<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mishʻam A stay in trouble or The saints rest in the evil day. Exactly discovered from their cordial dependance upon God, and comfortable assistance by him. Shortly digested as the saints manual in the worst of times. The first part. / By Alexander Pringle, a worthless servant to Christ in the work of his Gospel.</title>
            <author>Pringle, Alexander, of Harwich.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1592_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867765</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120089</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120089)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 201:E1592[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mishʻam A stay in trouble or The saints rest in the evil day. Exactly discovered from their cordial dependance upon God, and comfortable assistance by him. Shortly digested as the saints manual in the worst of times. The first part. / By Alexander Pringle, a worthless servant to Christ in the work of his Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Pringle, Alexander, of Harwich.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 73, [1], [8], 93, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Anne Maxey, for William Weekly at Ipswich, and are to be sold by John Rothwel, at the Fountain in Goldsmiths-Row in Cheap-side.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First line of title in Hebrew characters.</note>
                  <note>"Sōlangchna oiktirmōn: Bowels of mercie breathing for the saints in danger" has separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf = advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saints --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> A STAY in TROUBLE OR THE SAINTS REST IN THE <hi>EVIL DAY.</hi> Exactly diſcovered from their Cordial dependance upon God, and comfortable aſſiſtance by him. Shortly digeſted as the SAINTS MANUAL <hi>In the worſt of Times.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>FIRST PART.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Alexander Pringle,</hi> a worthleſs Servant to Chriſt in the work of his Goſpel.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thou haſt known my ſoul in adverſities.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 31.8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <l>The Lord was my ſtay.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 18.19.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <l>I ſaid thou art my God.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 31.14.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Anne Maxey,</hi> for <hi>William Weekly</hi> at <hi>Ipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Rothwel,</hi> at the Fountain in Goldſmiths-Row in Cheap-ſide. 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:2"/>
                  <head>To the moſt accompliſhed READER.</head>
                  <p>WOrthy Friend, (if ſuch) thy Perſonall Character will eaſily diſcover the Myſtery of this Manual: Seeing the wiſe Mans eyes are in his head, <hi>Eccleſ. 2.14.</hi> and the ſpiritual Man diſcerns all things, <hi>1 Cor. 2.15.</hi> Piety and Prudence, as they are of a ſacred Extraction, ſo they
<pb facs="tcp:120089:3"/>are of a ſearching Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>I confeſs here is <hi>(multum)</hi> not <hi>(multa)</hi> My (Genius) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſtomed to ſpeak rather much in a few, then little in many words.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt objected to thy <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a ſtay in trouble; together with the ſacred Sympathie of the Saints <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſealed in that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: If there be any thing ſeeming amiſs in the Draught of this Emblem, look again? There may be a dimneſs in the Optick, as a blemiſh in the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: The Eye and Color being
<pb facs="tcp:120089:3"/>often guilty of their active, and paſsive diſtempers: Let me on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell thee, ſeeing Wiſdom is juſtified of her Children: The truth of this Compendious Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, is more then ordinary careleſs of the trivial Cenſures of many.</p>
                  <p>But if any hath a Cordial appetite to peruſe it, I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them to befriend it, with a few of the choiceſt acts of their Intellect; otherwiſe, they may beat the Buſh, but never catch the Bird.</p>
                  <p>It ſhall facilitate ſomewhat the Exerciſe of their Fancy, to
<pb facs="tcp:120089:4"/>keep cloſe to the Subject, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing more of a ſecond (Notion) upon it, then what the (Being) of the firſt will bear.</p>
                  <p>Otherwiſe, if they trouble themſelves with an over-ſenſing Non-ſenſe; they may build Caſtles in the Air, but no way reaching the minde of the Author.</p>
                  <p>I have Candidly contrived a ſhort <hi>Syſtem</hi> of ſound words, for the eaſe of Troubled Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, if the gracious Sollidity of ſuch ſweetning Materials can ſettle their Condition, he
<pb facs="tcp:120089:4"/>hath his end, who zealouſly ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieth their Spiritual Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Truth and Peace; As</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Chriſts meaneſt Servant in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel,</hi> ALEX. PRINGLE.</signed>
                     <dateline>From my Study in <hi>Harwich,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Jan. 1. 1656.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:5"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>READER,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BE pleaſed, take notice, that the Eſcapes of the Preſs, are neither the Mind of the Author nor the Deſign of the Printer, and therefore let it be thy Civility to both, to excuſe the abſence of the one, and correct the unwilling Errata of the other.</p>
                  <div type="errata">
                     <head>Errata in the firſt Part.</head>
                     <p>Page 7. line 11. <hi>read</hi> as. p. 6. l. 1. <hi>r.</hi> Signing. p. 7. l. 1. <hi>r.</hi> as. p. 9. l. 20. <hi>r.</hi> ſay. p. 36. l. 1. <hi>r.</hi> but by him p. 39. l. 11. <hi>r.</hi> tedious.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="errata">
                     <head>Errata in the ſecond Part.</head>
                     <p>Page 5 line 13. <hi>r.</hi> viris. p. 9. l. 21. <hi>r.</hi> affectu. p. 10. l. 19. <hi>r.</hi> ſerie. p. 17. l. 13. <hi>r.</hi> Indemnity. p. 28. l. 15. <hi>r.</hi> Gallios. p. 38. l. 3. <hi>r.</hi> affectus. p. 39. l. 11. <hi>r.</hi> a me. p. 47. l. 9. <hi>r.</hi> it. p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. l. 22. <hi>r.</hi> holy. p. 62. l. 7. <hi>r.</hi> manu:</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:5"/>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>March 7. 1656.</date>
                     <signed>EDM. CALAMY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:6"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120089:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> A STAY in TROUBLE, OR THE SAINTS REST <hi>In the Evil Day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal. 63.8.</hi>
                        </bibl> My Soul cleaveth to thee, Thy right hand upholdeth me.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="introduction">
                     <head>Introduction.</head>
                     <p>IN the Compoſure and ſubject matter of this Pſalm,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hic Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>genere mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus ad loc.</note> we have a true account of the exerciſe of <hi>Davids</hi> Spirit, whileſt he was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120089:7"/>in the Wilderneſs of <hi>Ziph;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Sam. 23.14. Pſal. 57.2, 3.</note> It ſeems that place to him (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was in it ſelf) was a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of Prayer and Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p>Gracious Spirits can make the beſt of the baddeſt places,
<note place="margin">Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. Iſai. 26.3. Act. 5.41: 2 Cor. 6.10.</note> fair weather in the fouleſt ſtorms; they can turn raging troubles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Religious tryals, and a barren Wilderneſs in a Sanctuary of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.7, 8, 9, 10. Pſal. 42.5. Pſalm 73.28. Iſai. 40.29, 31.</note> It was <hi>Davids</hi> croſs to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, but his comfort and Crown to ſerve God in that eſtate.</p>
                     <p>He had a malicious <hi>Saul</hi> for his implacable enemy,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.15. 1 Sam. 26.1. Pſal. 52.8, 9.</note> but a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful God for his intimate Friend, he will not gratifie the one, to diſhonor the other; he will glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God whereſoever he ſojourn, let the Devil and <hi>Saul</hi> do what they can;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 54.6.</note>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 57.2.</note> they may baniſh him from the Tabernacle, and force
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120089:7"/>him to the Wilderneſs,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26, 19, 20. Pſal. 56.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> but not from Gods worſhip; they may afflict his body, but they are not able to pervert his Spirit:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.35, 36, 37. Pſalm 56.11, 12, 13.</note> For (ſaith he) <hi>My ſoul cleaveth to the Lord, his right hand upholdeth me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In which words we have two things materially conſiderable of <hi>Davids</hi> Spirit, as it is now enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in this diſconſolate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Its dependance upon God,
<note place="margin">The Text divided.</note> 
                        <hi>My ſoul cleaveth unto thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, Its aſſiſtance by God, <hi>His right hand upholdeth me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In both which parts,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> Saints ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in, trouble with God.</note> we may diſcern what a comfortable corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence is kept betwixt the Lord and <hi>David,</hi> in this ſad time; his heart cleaves to God, and the Lords hand upholds him; we ſhall conſider his words,
<note place="margin">The Text opened.</note> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> My ſoul, my whole Spirit,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120089:8"/>my life,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Plura au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem hoc vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulo fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificantur,</hi> 1. <hi>Spiritus.</hi> 2. <hi>Vita.</hi> 3. <hi>Anima rationalis.</hi> 4 <hi>Homo corpore, &amp; anima com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitus.</hi> 5 <hi>Per ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdochen perſonam fignificat.</hi> Saints careful of their ſpirits in trouble. Pſal. 56.3. Pſal. 7.2, 3. Amos. 6.8 Gen. 17.21 Lev. 19.28</note> the whole man as the root, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> originally import, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14.</p>
                     <p>Doubtleſs, <hi>David</hi> had nothing but what he had caſt upon God, in the caſe wherein he was; but eſpecially his perſon, which was more precious to him then all his other enjoyments; and it is the Saints cuſtom to ſpeak by their Spirits all things elſe, that being their <hi>(unum)</hi> their onely thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; if this be well placed, all things elſe are well preſerved: So <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh nothing here but his heart, and its eſtabliſhment upon God,
<note place="margin">Heb. Non ſimpliciter adherere ſignificat ſed aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gali affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu; quare, &amp; Rabbi David in radicibus per aſſociari ex ponit.</note> 
                        <hi>My ſoul cleaveth to God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Adhaeſit, adhereſcit anima mea poſt te,</hi> My ſoul cleaves after thee, as do things which hang by another; the root is of ſo great frequency in Scripture, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120089:8"/>of inquiry amongſt Criticks; it importeth here the poſture of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> ſpirit, and ſpeaketh it cloſe to God; and ſo depending upon him, as nothing could looſen it from him: Satans ſubtilty, <hi>Sauls</hi> cruelty; his own perſonal loſs and indemnity, are not all of them of any force or dexterity, to cut aſunder or unty the Gordian knot of this unity
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur hac voce arctiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum, &amp; indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum quale eſt inter conjuges.</hi> Gerh. loc. com.</note>.</p>
                     <p>The cleaving of <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit, was a glewing of the Lords ſpirit; a marriage of the Lords making, is altogether incapable of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels breaking.</p>
                     <p>It is no wonder, <hi>Davids</hi> words report him ſo much devoted to God,
<note place="margin">Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</note> ſeeing with the ſame breath they ſpeak him ſupported by God,
<note place="margin">Aſſiſtance.</note> 
                        <hi>Thy right hand</hi> (ſaith he.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Dextra tua,</hi> Thy right hand; This is a humane mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120089:9"/>feigning a Divine Power;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.16. Rev. 1.17. Pſal. 138.7. Pſal. 139.10. Pſal. 80.18.</note> it is ordinary for the Spirit to ſpeak low, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, for our infirmity that we may conceive <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> (in a Divine decency) according to our capacity.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Right hand]</hi> In Scripture Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, when attributed to God ſometime ſignifieth God himſelf, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 48.13. His word, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.8. His preſent aid and aſſiſtance, <hi>Pſal</hi> 74.11. All which may be underſtood by this right hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding <hi>David</hi> in this juncture of time.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Suſtentat me,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exprimit ad jumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta omnia &amp; admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula quibus pollere ſibi videtur.</hi> A word ſignifying not onely the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of body, but alſo of minde.</note> He often or always upholdeth me: This ſeems to be a Phraſe of <hi>Davids</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he had taſted that the Lord was good in that and other his ſuffering ſeaſons.</p>
                     <p>The Saints are ſenſible of their ſupplies, and reſent them: The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120089:9"/>veſſels of mercy are all ſo thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> Pſal. 116.3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> as faithful obſervers of Gods favor;
<note place="margin">Deut. 8.11. Pſal. 119.16. Pſal. 103.2.</note> they vent none of their receipts, but in reſpective ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements.</p>
                     <p>It is not with them, as it is with thoſe hollow Ciſterns of this degenerous. Generation, whoſe worthleſs Genius ſpeak them ſuch as they are; under the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent kindneſſes, all ſo ſenſleſs as thankleſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> it ſeems is of another more refined Spirit,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> The thank fulneſs of the Saints.</note> he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly publiſh thoſe mutual out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goings of Spirit and power, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Lord and himſelf, and tell the world, that his enemies may hear his ſoul cleaved to God, and the Lord did uphold him.</p>
                     <p>Such Religious tidings might cool the courage of his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, they hearing he was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120089:10"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:120089:10"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:120089:11"/>joyned to ſo ſtrong a party, who was able to ſupport him and bear him up,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.13, 17. &amp; 24.22.</note> in oppoſition to all their deſigned ſtratagems complotted or executed againſt him.</p>
                     <p>HAving thus ſhortly taken a ſurvey of <hi>Davids</hi> words; I finde they preſent the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular deportment and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his own,
<note place="margin">The reſult of the words.</note> or any other gracious ſpirit in trouble, and thus in two eminent conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> Such a gracious ſpirit hath its total dependance upon God.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, It hath a comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able aſſiſtance from Cod.</p>
                     <p>In theſe two ſtreams flow all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120089:11"/>the ſubſtantial ſweetneſs of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> words in this place.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, They give us in the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit cleaving to God.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, They report his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental aſſiſtance in the evil day by him; we ſhall ſpeak to each of theſe in their order.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>I. <hi>Of the Saints De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt, That a gracious ſpirit hath its total dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God in trouble, ſeems to be <hi>Davids</hi> caſe and qualification in this eſtate.</p>
                     <p>He was ſharply aſſaulted by <hi>Saul,</hi> but ſtrictly united to God; <hi>My ſoul cleaveth to God: Adhaerendi verbum</hi> (ſays <hi>Calvin</hi>) <hi>ſignificat David
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120089:12"/>cor ſuum firma perſeverantia ſemper af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixum fore Deo.</hi> Cal. ad loc.</p>
                     <p>Troubles lay hold upon <hi>David,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Davids</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom. Pſal. 11.1. Pſal. 25.1.</note> and <hi>Davids</hi> Spirit lays hold upon his God: It is worth Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, he caſts not of his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but caſts himſelf and his burthen upon God: My foul, ſuch as it is, my perſecuted, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſoul cleaveth to the Lord: Here <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth an abſolute dependance upon God,
<note place="margin">Diodate.</note> ſays <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date in loc.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Temporal ſufferings for God,
<note place="margin">Troubles unite, and not divide ſaints from God.</note> are ſpiritual ſodderings of the Saints Spirits to him: Such an Antiperiſtaſis begets a Religious heat in a gracious heart, burning their corruptions, and melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their affections upon God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.28.</p>
                     <p>Afflictions work kindly upon the Spirits of the Godly;
<note place="margin">Note.</note> it was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120089:12"/>good for me (ſaid <hi>David</hi>) that I was afflicted:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> Afflictions work di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly upon Saints and Sinners.</note> Croſſes are Cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives to ſome, but Cordials to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     <p>There is no ſtomack can down with calamity,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14. 2 Cor. 6.10. Pſal. 56.10, 11. Pſal. 56.3.</note> ſo well as that which is appetized with mercy; ſuch ſpirits are more the Lords then their own,
<note place="margin">The Saints reſt in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. Iſa. 54.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</note> and therefore in ſtorms can reſt upon him, like the Dove upon the Ark, or the Ark upon <hi>Arrarat;</hi> he is the higheſt and ſureſt mountain, and can ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle us in the deepeſt deluge:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> Whether afflictions ſend or lead the Saints.</note> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I have obſerved the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures ſpeak much of the Saints motion, and tendency of their ſpirits in trouble, and I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſeen them turn into this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of refuge, and take hold of the horns of this Altar: I read <hi>David</hi> praiſing God, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 18.2. By the Phraſeology of a Rock, Fortreſſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120089:13"/>Strength, Truſt, Shield, and horn of his Salvation: And elſewhere, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 23. he priſeth his preſence ſo much, that although he ſhould walk in the valley of the ſhadow of death, he feared no evil, he was with him, his rod and ſtaff comforted him.</p>
                     <p>Bt it ſeems there is no love loſt betwixt the Lord and his ſervants in trouble;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> The ſweet correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Lord and his people.</note> for he is with them whileſt they are with him, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.2.
<note place="margin">Saints more happy then the wicked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way.</note> Thus the Saints are happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in their croſſes then the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in their comforts; the firſt may be enjoyed with God, the ſecond without him.</p>
                     <p>But to winde up all what is here reported of <hi>David,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note. Davids</hi> practice, and all the Saints the ſame.</note> I finde it is the Language and Learning of all the godly in his caſe; as they are of the ſame ſpirit and intereſt,
<note place="margin">In affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> ſo they are of the ſame practice
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120089:13"/>and profeſſion, to depend upon a gracious God in trouble.</p>
                     <p>There be three reaſons amongſt many,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note</hi> Hence the arguments of the Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> obliging the Saints to a dependance upon God in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Their accompliſhment.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, Their incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, Their eſtabliſhment in that eſtate.</p>
                     <p>It ſeems as the Saints cannot be troubled without God, ſo they can confidently look upon him for all their ſupplies and furniture in that their ſad condition.</p>
                     <p>We ſhall take notice of thoſe prementioned grounds in their order.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. Saints ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Deſcribed what it is.</note> Of the Saints accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from their dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God in trouble.</p>
                     <p>The Saints accompliſhment is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120089:14"/>their gracious qualification, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming their Intereſt, adding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to their Eſſence, but to their Ornament,
<note place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> putting a fitneſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to ſerve God in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> The decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Saints ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in adverſity. Pſal. 97.8.10, 11.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>That this accompliſhment is very ſuitable to the Saints, and ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to them in trouble, from their dependance upon God is eaſie to finde out, if we ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Particulars following.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">The grounds of accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in trouble.</note> Troubles are the Saints tryals, and there is nothing more becoming them in that eſtate, then to act like themſelves,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.1.2, 3.</note> that by their carriage they may confute their calamity,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.12. 2. <hi>Ground.</hi>
                        </note> and the abetters of it.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, There is a dextrous activity neceſſary in trouble, which at other times is uſeleſſe: The Mariner in a Tempeſt muſt ſtand to his Tackling, when in a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120089:14"/>calm he may ſleep.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground. </seg>3</label> It is one of the trueſt Characters of worth, to manage every condition with advantage; not that gain is the honor of our actions,
<note place="margin">Preoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</note> but that thus all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are gainers of honor.</p>
                     <p>Now as to theſe the Saints ſhould come eminently ſhort, if they were not fixed upon God, and therefore they cleave to him for accompliſhment, when (in ſuch a ſeaſon) they have none in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
<note place="margin">Depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon God neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and profitable.</note> And they finde their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God is not labor in vain; God hath ingaged his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe more then once or twice for the profit of this poſture, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 26.3. With an aſſured purpoſe wilt thou preſerve perfect peace, becauſe they truſted in thee: Here is peace deſigned by God to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending ſoul upon him; the like
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120089:15"/>is promiſed often elſewhere, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.22. <hi>If ye cleave to him, then will the Lord caſt out the Nations before you:</hi> Here we may read Iſrael will be too hard for his enemies, if he can be happy in holding faſt his trueſt Friend. The God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is the giver of every good gift, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. There is no fear of Proviſion if he be our Steward, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11, 12.</p>
                     <p>Hence it comes,
<note place="margin">Grace the Saints riches, and the Saints are happy in trouble by their Graces.</note> the Saints are richer in adverſity, then are the wicked in their proſperity; they have more precious furniture in one corner of their hearts, then the wicked in the whole Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of their ſpirits, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.4.</p>
                     <p>The godly have not onely the exerciſe,
<note place="margin">Graces great in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</note> but the increaſe of their Graces in trouble; for they reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> Inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Graces in affliction.</note> they are recruited and enlarged by him. Hence it comes, their Faith is more lively,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120089:15"/>their hope more heavenly, their Love more fervent, their Wiſdom more vigilant, their Patience more permanent, their Prudence more provident, their Piety more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent, whileſt they labor in that eſtate.</p>
                     <p>Theſe diſtinguiſhing Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of accompliſhment,
<note place="margin">Graces manifeſted by trouble.</note> have been written upon the Lords wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies in the days of their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, that they might ſhine as ſo many memorial Monuments to poſterity of future obſervance; that as it is the Saints lot to be troubled,
<note place="margin">Saints no loſers by trouble.</note> ſo it is their happineſs to be no loſers in that eſtate, by their dependance upon God; it ſeems it is the Saints communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, that ſweetens that condition.
<note place="margin">No lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon our ſelves in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The godly ſhould be hardly put to it, if they did lean upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120089:16"/>
                        <hi>David</hi> was a great deal more happy by cleaving to his God, then <hi>Saul</hi> and all his favor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites truſting upon man.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>David</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wits his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, by his depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God.</note> And herein he was wiſer then all his enemies which complotted his ruine; he knew he was not onely out of their reach, when he reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon God, but fully accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated with all things befitting his condition; he was with ſuch a Friend, who would ſpare no coſt in his keeping,
<note place="margin">To cloſe with God is the Saints ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in trouble.</note> and therefore to keep cloſe to him was his ſureſt and ſweeteſt courſe he could take in trouble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73, <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is the excellency of <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit, that he is contented to be any where with God;
<note place="margin">The godly are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be with God any where.</note> He can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the wearineſſe of a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by the comfort of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: Gods preſence makes every place alike, and is inſtead of all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120089:16"/>Injoyments to the godly, and it is no wonder they ſhould be ſo ſatisfied with him, ſeeing he is ſo precious or profitable to them, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 37.39, 40.</p>
                     <p>Let this piece of <hi>Davids</hi> and the godlies practice bear witneſſe,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applica∣tion. </seg>
                        </label> that it is not a matter indifferent to depend upon, or cleave unto God in the evil day, but that it is an act of ſingular advantage, both in reſpect of themſelves and their adverſaries; it ſeems both are gainers and loſers in this very thing.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Saints are gainers by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God.</note> It is the Saints gain to depend upon God, becauſe of their furniture: They ſhould be as other men in trouble, if they were not happy in thoſe things which they receive from God, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 31.19. <hi>How great is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which thou haſt laid up for them</hi>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:120089:17"/>that fear thee, and done to them that truſt in thee before the ſons of men: Here the Spirit of God will have us take notice of two things,</p>
                     <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">The Saints mercy is expected by them.</note> That the godly have more then ordinary favor in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, They are ſuch as depend and attend upon that goodneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are loſers.</note> For the Saints adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries; That they are loſers, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherways fall out, if the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be gainers; But ſo it is, the godly being joyned to God, they are accurately fitted by God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter their enemies.
<note place="margin">Divine depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance doth ſtrengthen the Saints.</note> 
                        <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly;</hi> It is not for the enemies of the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ingage againſt God.</p>
                     <p>Me thinks all this,
<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> and much more, might give warning to the Saints to fear none of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, when they have the Lord
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120089:17"/>upon their ſide, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>If God be for us</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>who can be againſt us.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have obſerved the godly to be patient in their Afflictions,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> An obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the ſaints deportment in trouble, whileſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon God.</note> Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in their tranſactions, Pious in their perſecutions, Peaceable under injuries, Humble under indignities, and hopeful of their deliverances; All which, as ſo many extractions from their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God.</p>
                     <p>It is the worſt of non-ſence,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> to ſay we can be cloſe by the fire, and not finde warmth; and by the ſea, and not finde water: Such may be the folly of thoſe who i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine a ſoul united to God, and not qualified in trouble ſuitable to its eſtate.</p>
                     <p>I confeſs,
<note place="margin">The ſaints ſingular carriage in this world.</note> when I ſee the Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment in the world, I am apt to admire at their ſingularity, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120089:18"/>they are neither in Principle or Practice like the world; and when I ſee they are no more ſtrangers to ſome of the wickeds perſons, then to all of the wickeds practice and carriage in trouble; I conſider that there is ſomething more then ordinary acting in them, whileſt they are in that eſtate; and when I have made a ſerious inquiry, I can finde nothing but their clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to God;
<note place="margin">Union with God makes the Saints of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweet beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior in the world, to the good example of all.</note> that eſtabliſhment of their ſpirits upon him, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth them not onely conſiderable in the eyes of their enemies, but eminently profitable to themſelves and others of their Intereſt.</p>
                     <p>For the nearer they are to God, the more accompliſhment they have from him:
<note place="margin">Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers us from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions.</note> So that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are eaſed of all their inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Incumbrances, if they reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. The conſideration of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120089:18"/>which, moved <hi>Peter</hi> when he writ to all the Saints, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. To counſel them to caſt all their care upon him, for he cared for them; words of ſingular uſe for the godly in trouble, to attend proviſion in ſuch a ſeaſon,
<note place="margin">Help to be expected from God, when there is none vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</note> when there is none to be ſeen: When the black curtain of calamity is drawn about them, and all ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary helps ſeparate from them, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.19. Such was <hi>Davids</hi> caſe in this deſert, wherein he had no reſerve but his God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſoul cleaveth to him: <hi>My ſoul cleaveth to thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">
                           <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Of the Saints dependance upon God.</note> there is another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ground of <hi>Davids</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon his God; and this is his incouragement in trouble.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> had need of incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his now ſad condition;
<note place="margin">Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in trouble.</note> it ſeems he had many cruel ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120089:19"/>but few cordial Friends; and therefore he thought it beſt to make ſure of God,
<note place="margin">Saints ſure of comfort if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon God in trouble.</note> and then he knew to be ſure of continued comfort, whatever ſhould betide him.</p>
                     <p>This was not onely an act of <hi>Davids</hi> Piety, but of his ſingular Prudence and Policy; He was no ſtranger to the Lords tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe over him, and all the godly acting for both: <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is amongſt them that uphold my ſoul,</hi> Pſalm 54.4. It would ſeem the Lord makes a party for <hi>David</hi> in the midſt of his Enemies.</p>
                     <p>It had gone hard with him if Satan had got his minde;
<note place="margin">Saints ſhould be in a ſad condition if the Lord did not own them in trouble.</note> he would not onely have ſtript him of all his accompliſhment, but alſo of all his incouragements.</p>
                     <p>By the firſt, Unfitting him to ſuffer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:120089:19"/>
By the ſecond, Undoing him in that eſtate.</p>
                     <p>But I finde <hi>Davids</hi> dependance upon God, diſpels all ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements; he was certain that Satan or any of his Inſtruments could not wrong him, if the Lord did ſtand his friend; <hi>I truſt in God</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 56.11.) <hi>I fear not what man can do unto me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> had an enemy (which in reſpect of his place and pravity of ſpirit,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Davids</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies of a curſed and cruel ſpirit, and bent to undoe him.</note> as the times preſented) might have dampt his courage, he being then in a capacity to do him a great deal of miſchief; but this ſealed Saint, being in league with God, he valued not his wrath; for he apprehended his ſecurity from that unity betwixt God and his ſpirit: <hi>My ſoul</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth unto God, his right hand uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:120089:20"/>
The Saints dependance upon God in trouble, doth afford vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous incouragements to them in that eſtate,
<note place="margin">The Saints incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in trouble.</note> but eſpecially,</p>
                     <p>Firſt, His preſence with them.</p>
                     <p>Second, His Providence over them.</p>
                     <p>Third, Honor to their Friends.</p>
                     <p>Fourth, Shame to their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
                     <p>Fifth, Shortneſs of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
                     <p>Sixth, Sweetneſſe of Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,
<note n="1" place="margin">Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</note> The Saints dependance upon God aſſures them of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: <hi>I am always with thee</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>I have ſet the Lord at my right hand,</hi> Pſalm. 16 8.</p>
                     <p>It is not hard to finde out <hi>Gods</hi> preſence with his ſervants in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by their dependance upon him; And I conceive, the Lord
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120089:20"/>is pleaſed to incourage his ſervants thus, by countenancing of them, that they may reliſh his favor, which they account better then life.
<note place="margin">Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the Saints pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative.</note> Thus he will not have his ſervants to be troubled at the fury of their Adverſaries, whilſt they have him to be friend.</p>
                     <p>Hence it is, that the godly do ſo much prize him,
<note place="margin">God the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone help of the Saints.</note> that they look after no aſſiſtance with him; his preſence is ſuch a cordial preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to ſecure them, that they are almoſt careleſs of any power whatſoever to oppoſe them: This incouragement, I conceive, may prove profitable to all of <hi>Davids</hi> intereſt, if they ingenuouſly deſire the Lords preſence with them;
<note place="margin">Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance is bleſſed with the Lords preſence.</note> they muſt conclude to fix their ſpirits upon him, then they need not queſtion but he will hide them privily in his preſence
<note place="margin">Pſal 31.20.</note>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:120089:21"/>from the pride of men.</p>
                     <p>Secondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</note> The Saints have the incouragement of the Lords pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence acting for them, when their ſpirits depend upon him; it is not the Lords cuſtom to forget or neglect thoſe who are in unity with himſelf, he hath an eye to look out for them, as they have a heart to lay hold upon him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 17.7.</p>
                     <p>Hence the godly are not much troubled in adverſity for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; they conclude (ſeeing the Lord is their Shepherd) they cannot want; <hi>He maketh them reſt in green paſtures, and leadeth them by the ſtill waters;</hi> ſo that they may know their unity with <hi>God</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them happy, in the hardſhip of any eſtate whatſoever: Gods gracious providence over them, is ſuch an incouragement to them,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120089:21"/>as both ſanctifieth and ſeaſoneth their trouble, and their ſpirits un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</p>
                     <p>Let this incouragement quicken Saints, but damp ſinners,
<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> whilſt both ſuffer in the evil day; Let it aſſure the firſt, that they are not alone in adverſity, whilſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond are deſolutely drowned in the fainting fits of their own ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful calamity.</p>
                     <p>Third incouragement of Saints,
<note place="margin">Third in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> depending upon their God in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is the honor of their friends: The Saints as they are a choſen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, ſo they are of the ſame mutual intereſt and honor.</p>
                     <p>It is not ſo much a matter of private, as publick concernment, that they depend upon God; thus they ſtand in the face of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<note place="margin">Saints ſtand or falito their brethren.</note> to their brethren as to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: For the Churches credit is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120089:22"/>common as to all, ſo to each particular member of that body: It is no ſmall incouragement to the godly,
<note place="margin">Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the godly to ſee their party proſper.</note> to ſee their party proſper in deſpight of malice, they are delighted in the Saints honor as their own; and therefore in the day of trouble they depend upon God, that the Saints be no loſers by them, and that all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may know the godly have credit and comfort in their ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conflicts, both for themſelves and friends, let the devil do what he can: <hi>All this is come upon us, yet do we not forget thee, neither deal we falſly concerning thy Covenant,</hi> Pſalm 44.17.</p>
                     <p>It ſhould not onely be the ſhame,
<note place="margin">The godly are troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their brethrens calamity, for their common concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> but the ſorrow of Saints to ſee their brethren betray their common intereſt to the will of the wicked, by making ſhipwrack of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120089:22"/>their integrity upon the breaches of their trouble;
<note place="margin">Depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon God, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative of the Saints integrity.</note> and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can preſerve them from ſuch an adventure, but to be much with God; their unity with him, doth fit and compleatly furniſh them with an accompliſhment and ſweet incouragement in every eſtate; ſo that in the worſt of times, their deportment may nor onely be a happineſs to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but an honor to all their friends.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly,
<note n="4" place="margin">Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Saints ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> it is no ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the Saints, to ſee God turn his hand againſt their enemies; that as they have been ſcourged by them, he is pleaſed to caſt the rod in the fire: God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways gratifies his ſervants thus when they depend upon him; he can clothe their enemies with ſhame, that they may ſee their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:120089:23"/>deſires upon them.</p>
                     <p>The Scripture tells us, The Lord will have the credit of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity to fall at laſt to the ſhare of the Saints, but the curſe to their enemies; that although the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hath ſown their miſery,
<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſow what they do not reap.</note> yet they ſhall never be able to reap their ruine, no not ſo much as the leaſt of comfort or honor in their diſturbance; it is juſt with God to trouble them who trouble you, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6.</p>
                     <p>Therefore the godly caſt their caſe upon God,
<note place="margin">God the avenger.</note> and he takes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with their enemies to ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; they cannot ſeek ſo much honor to themſelves, or ſhame to their adverſaries, as the Lord will heap upon both.</p>
                     <p>This (me thinks) ſhould warn the wicked to minde themſelves when they malign the Saints:
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                        </label>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:120089:23"/>For if they prove inſolent over the godly by an (Ace) another caſt of the Dy of Providence, may Sink their condition.</p>
                     <p>Fifthly,
<note n="5" place="margin">Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</note> Shortneſs in trouble is another incouragement to the Saints from their dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God; and this is the Lords work, and the Saints benefit:
<note place="margin">Depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon God ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the Saints trouble.</note> It ſeems they obtain ſuch favor from him, when they are in unity with him: It is eaſie with God to make an end of the Saints Calamity, if they reſt upon him, for the Saints croſſes are like <hi>Samſons</hi> cords, they are quickly broken if the Lord do but ſtrain them;
<note place="margin">Simile or compariſon</note> it is but a poor tryal of the Lords ability, to eaſe the Saints of their ſufferings, he can do that for them and never trouble himſelf: Therefore it hath been his practice to diſpatch their calamity like a cloud, if their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120089:24"/>did ſix upon him;
<note place="margin">Exo. 14.13</note> how ſoon is <hi>Pharaoh</hi> drowned, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtandeth ſtill to behold the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his God?</p>
                     <p>I apprehend this is no courſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement which the Saints have from God, when their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits cleave unto him; it ſeems he maketh an end of their troubles to the beſt advantage.</p>
                     <p>Therefore I conclude it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the Saints to ſettle upon God in their ſaddeſt condition;
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applica∣tion. </seg>
                        </label> this hath been accounted the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ſhorteſt and ſureſt way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine their troubles;
<note place="margin">2 Chro. 20.12, 22, 23, 24, 25.</note> they have truſted the Lord with their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and he hath always brought their purpoſes to a deſiderable period.</p>
                     <p>It is the Saints happineſs to be happy in this, that they have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to depend upon God, more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:120089:24"/>then upon any thing elſe below him,
<note place="margin">The Saints know what the Lord can do for them by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments.</note> for they are certain he can imploy any inſtrument to befriend them, if they did caſt themſelves upon him.</p>
                     <p>Sixthly and laſtly,
<note n="6" place="margin">Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, a gracious deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> It is not the leaſt incouragement to the godly after a tedious trouble, to be ſure of a gracious deliverance.</p>
                     <p>It ſeaſoneth the bitterneſs of former calamity, to have a few grains of mercy mingled in their future recovery;
<note place="margin">The Saints forget their troubles, &amp; forgive their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies when they are delivered.</note> and therefore the godly being delivered, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſeal a Bill of oblivion to all their former ſufferings upon that account.</p>
                     <p>There is no better way to obtain this comfortable benefit from God, then by a confident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon him: For as there is no evil in the City without God, ſo there is no deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:120089:25"/>from it by him.</p>
                     <p>Hence the godly have this their incouragement amongſt the reſt, that they do rely upon God for a glorious deliverance; from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their deepeſt ingagements in it, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.9. he will bring me forth unto the light, and I ſhall ſee his righteouſneſs.</p>
                     <p>The Saints caſe ſhould be very diſmal and miſerably dark, if they did not ſee ſomewhat coming, which did ſweeten their preſent condition; and therefore they look for this as an incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their dependance upon God, to have a gracious deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from him.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall need adde no more:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Davids</hi> practice our pattern in the evil day.</note> 
                        <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> is a notable pattern of this kinde of practice: <hi>My foul</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>cleaveth to thee:</hi> He fixeth his ſpirit upon God, aſſuring himſelf
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:120089:25"/>if he did ingage his heart to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious dependance upon him, he was certain of a comfortable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance by him; and ſo much we have ſpoken of <hi>Davids,</hi> and all the Saints their incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from their dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God.</p>
                     <p>The third ground of the Saints their dependance upon God in trouble,
<note n="3" place="margin">Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of ſpirit.</note> is their eſtabliſhment ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, whilſt they are laboring under the preſſure of that diſmal eſtate.</p>
                     <p>It is not onely a convenient, but a qualification abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Saints intereſt, to be of an eſtabliſhed ſpirit.</p>
                     <p>This piece of compoſure ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what they are,
<note place="margin">Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a character of Saints.</note> both in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and Practice; and there is nothing can put or keep a ſoul in this poſture, but its dependance
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:120089:26"/>upon God, when the ſoul is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored upon him; it is fully fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ride out unchangeably the fury of any ſtorm,
<note place="margin">Satan Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the Saints trouble to unfix them.</note> 
                        <hi>Pſalm</hi> 46.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. It is Satans Maſter piece to improve the Saints afflictions to inconſtancy of ſpirit; thus making his beſt advantage of their worſt and weakeſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</p>
                     <p>If he can but ſhake them from their piety, he is then ſure to break them by his policy, and therefore he is as vigilant as malicious to effectuate their ruine.</p>
                     <p>The godly have nothing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent him, but to cloſe with their God; prizing more his preſence with them, then the enmity of all created powers acting againſt them.</p>
                     <p>This is viſibly legible in <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit, who is careful in nothing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120089:26"/>but to own his God; and he knew that the keeping of a familiar Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with him, ſhould ſoon eaſe him of all his adverſaries, he tels all of them of whatſoever impreſſion they were, <hi>his ſoul cleaved to God.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons put the Saints to it.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>It was an hard time with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> the waves of wickedneſſe did waſh upon his Spirit, yet we ſee this tedoius Tempeſt did not drive it from its Anchor: <hi>David</hi> is of a ſtable heart in the midſt of thoſe Diſtractions; his enemies could do nothing upon his inward, whatever breach they did make upon his outward eſtate; it ſeems he ſecures his Soul with God what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever befel him.
<note place="margin">Satan more pleaſed to pervert the ſpirits, then to impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eſtates of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>I confeſſe it would have pleaſed the Devil better to have made <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> a ſinful Sceptick in this his Calamity, then to ſee him a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:120089:27"/>Saint, to have made him of no Religion as to God, then of no Eſtate as to the World; to have ſtript him rather of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Conſcience, then of the glory of his Kingdom.
<note place="margin">Satan pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>But herein <hi>David</hi> outwits his Policy, and outworks his Power, he takes ſuch a Comfortable courſe with his Spirit, as Satan could neither unſettle it, or unſeal its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrety; he caſts it upon God, and ſo firmly ſecures it in oppoſition to any Change whatſoever, let Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan or all of his Inſtruments do their worſt.</p>
                     <p>So much we have conſidered of the Saints Dependance upon their God in trouble, according to this pattern of <hi>Davids</hi> practiſe, <hi>My Soul cleaveth to God.</hi> We ſhall further inquire into the ſecond Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:120089:27"/>
                     <head>II. <hi>Of the Saints Aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT appears by <hi>Davids</hi> words here, and elſewhere,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Note.</hi> Saints aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance a fruit of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God.</note> that the Saints aſſiſtance from God, is a fruit of their dependance upon him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Our fathers truſted in thee</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>and were delivered, they tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in thee, and were not confounded,</hi> Pſal. 22.4, 5.</p>
                     <p>There is an old correſpondance of kindneſs kept betwixt the Lord and his ſervants; as they look upon him for their furniture in adverſity; ſo he upon the frame and poſture of their ſpirits expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it:
<note place="margin">God wil be ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> 
                        <hi>The Lord is good and a ſtrong hold in the day of trouble; but</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>he knoweth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:120089:28"/>them that truſt in him,</hi> Nahum 1.7.</p>
                     <p>The godly conſider the Lords aſſiſtance to be the beſt;
<note place="margin">Gods help the beſt &amp; moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as that which is moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and precious, it is deſired by them. I find <hi>David</hi> and others of the godly in the Scriptures to look upon this divine help as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted often from means. <hi>I do not truſt in my bow, neither can my ſword ſave me, but thou haſt ſaved us,</hi> Pſal 44.6, 7.</p>
                     <p>As means are not the objects of the Saints confidence, ſo they know without the Lord they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the ſubject of their aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.
<note place="margin">Saints rely not upon means.</note> 
                        <hi>If the Lord had not holpen me,</hi> (Pſal. 94.17) <hi>my ſoul had almoſt dwelt in ſilence, when I ſaid my foot ſlideth, thy mercy ſtayed me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is a Caveat put in againſt all means by the Spirit,
<note place="margin">Caveat.</note> that they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120089:28"/>rob not God of his honour;
<note place="margin">Depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon means, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage God</note> and therefore the Saints give no more to them then he hath allotted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> they know they only act in their ſervice,
<note place="margin">Means are acted by God only, and not of themſelves</note> as they are ordered by God; and that there is no more of any ability in them, then what the Lord hath diſpenced, therefore the godly look upon the Lords hand as the hope of their help, in trouble, <hi>thy right hand upholdeth me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So then the Lord is the only help,
<note place="margin">As the Saints look upon God, ſo he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon them.</note> and grand aſſiſtant of his Saints, and their eyes in trouble are upon him; which aſpect, as it ſignifieth the excellency of the Lords favour to them, ſo it ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the unity of their ſpirits with him, <hi>In the multitude of the thoughts of my heart, thy comforts rejoiced my ſoul,</hi> Pſal. 94.19.</p>
                     <p>Here is <hi>Davids</hi> familiarity with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120089:29"/>God, and his refreſhment given in to him, in the juncture of his trouble.</p>
                     <p>And it may be witneſſed by the experience of all the godly, that this is not only his,
<note place="margin">Gods help the portion of all the godly.</note> but the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Saints, therefore ſhall every one that is godly, make his prayer to thee in a time when thou maiſt be found. <hi>Surely in the floods of great waters they will not come neer him,</hi> Pſal. 32.6.</p>
                     <p>It ſeems it is the Lords cuſtom, for the Saints exceeding comfort, to ingage for them when they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat him in trouble;
<note place="margin">God wil be entreated for his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath commanded them to pray, that he might engage for them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call upon me;</hi> There is here ſomewhat notable, that the godly muſt not fail to cal if they expect the Lord to anſwer, or to do any thing for them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:120089:29"/>
Me thinks I need not put the Reader to any further coſt of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering many more Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Preocupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> which ſpeak home the truth of the Lords aſſiſtance to his Saints in <hi>Davids</hi> caſe. Let us only take the Affidavit of one Scripture more to this purpoſe, <hi>Iſai</hi> 41.10. <hi>Feare not for I am with thee, be not afraid, for I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee, I will ſuſtain thee with my right hand of Juſtice.</hi> Here I conceive the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet hath commiſſion to ſpeak the Lords mind fully to his people in order to their comfort and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in trouble, and that he may do it to purpoſe he crowds in the vaſt body of the Lords benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to them in a Nutſhel. And ſo he is pleaſed to ſpeak much in little, and but a little of much, Ingroſſing a ſum of aſſurances, in the ſyſteme of a few promiſes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120089:30"/>for their eſtabliſhment.</p>
                     <p>It is a great comfort, which is able to ſettle the ſpirit of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in trouble, when they know what the Lord will do for them.</p>
                     <p>And in this very point of the Saints Information,
<note place="margin">It is the Saints comfort to know God to be their friend.</note> he is pleaſed to priviledg them above the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in adverſity. He opens their eyes, not only to let them ſee their mercy, but himſelf the fountaine of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I will lift up my eyes</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>to the mountaines, from whence my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation cometh, my help cometh from the name of the Lord.</hi> This was <hi>Davids</hi> diſtinguiſhing mercy, that in the midſt of his miſery, he could ſee his remedy, and the Lord his Phyſitian.</p>
                     <p>So then the difference betwixt ſuffering Saints and ſinners lieth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:120089:30"/>in this,
<note place="margin">Difference betwixt Saints and ſinners in trouble.</note> the Lord engageth for the aſſiſtance of the one, and not for the other. So that the wicked are left hopeleſs and helpleſs in the evil day, when the godly find a favourable and gracious ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in that ſeaſon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thy right hand upholdeth me,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> This is a word of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and ſo much the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures witneſſe of all the godly, that the Lord doth engage for them. But upon what grounds he up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds the Saints againſt their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,
<note place="margin">Grounds of the Lords aſſiſtance for his Saints.</note> is the thing further now to be inquired after.</p>
                     <p>I find the Scriptures give in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple teſtimony of the Lords ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for, and ſupporting of his people in trouble,
<note place="margin">Eight grounds of the Lords aſſiſtance.</note> and ſo do move us to conſider of eight reaſons of his undertaking for them.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, We read of an eminently
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:120089:31"/>intimate intereſt he hath in them,
<note place="margin">Ground of the Lords help his intereſt</note> ſo that they are honoured with the names of ſtricteſt relation, union and communion with himſelf,
<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> as of his Spouſe, Children, Brethren, to his Son Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Exod. 19.5</note> his <hi>chiefeſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure above all people in the earth;</hi> and with the characters of greateſt worth as can be put upon ſuch, as, <hi>a choſen generation,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9, 10</note> a royal Prieſthood, a holy Nation, a people ſet at liberty; in times paſt not a people, but now the people of God; in times paſt not under mercy; but now obtained mercy, &amp;c.</hi> By all which we underſtand thoſe ſaving rights he hath to his Saints by Election,
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.4, 5 1 Cor. 1.30</note> Vocation, Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Juſtification, Sanctification and Glory.</p>
                     <p>This Intereſt laid in the bottom,
<note place="margin">Intereſt the ground of aſſiſtance.</note> upon it is built the whole Fabrick of the Lords favour both in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity and adverſity to the godly.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:120089:31"/>So that they are put in a more then ordinary ſecurity of obtaining whatſoever is neceſſary, for their comfortable aſſiſtance and ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in any eſtate. I remember, <hi>David</hi> tels us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10. <hi>That the beaſts of prey may be ſtarved when the Saints ſhall have plenty.</hi> The inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt which the Lord hath in the Saints,
<note place="margin">Intereſt makes the Saints pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</note> as it is the ground of his act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, ſo it renders them precious to him, as a ſeal upon his heart, or a ſignet upon his arme. And it is not to be queſtioned, but the Saints find the ſweetneſſe of it in their ſharpeſt conflicts.
<note place="margin">Saints dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to God then their parents.</note> 
                        <hi>Though my father and mother forſake me, yet the Lord will gather me up,</hi> Pſal. 27.10. And therefore the Lord profeſſeth, that the caſe of his people is alwaies before him, when they apprehend (by their eſtate) that they are negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14, 15, 16.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:120089:32"/>
This intereſt is the binding bond of matrimonial unity and amity betwixt the Lord and his people,
<note place="margin">Intereſt the marriage bond of Saints.</note> 
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 19.20. <hi>I have married thee, &amp;c.</hi> Perſons married are cemented with all the ſoddering and ſweetning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of conjugal correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence either in proſperity or adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
                     <p>Hence I find this intereſt to be very ſerviceable to the ſaints in their ſuffering ſeaſons. It is the Altar upon which they ſacrifice the Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their addreſſes to God when they are put to their utmoſt,
<note place="margin">Intereſt the Altar of our duties to God.</note> 
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.15, 16. <hi>Look down from heaven, and behold, from the dwelling place of thy holineſs, &amp;c. Where is thy zeal and thy ſtrength, and the multitude of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and of thy compaſsions? they are reſtrained. Doubtleſs thou art our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Iſrael know us not.</hi> Here is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:120089:32"/>addreſs upon intereſt put up to God. It is no wonder the ſaints ſhould be earneſt upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
<note place="margin">Intereſt the ground of the Saints correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> ſeeing the moſt ſolid ground of that mutual correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Lord and his people, and therefore to be improved in the worſt of times.</p>
                     <p>Oh then let this be remembred by all the heires of heaven in the dark day of their danger,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                        </label>
                        <note place="margin">Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</note> when the clouds of calamity are dropping o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them here upon earth, that there may be a ſpirit of wiſdom acting in them,
<note place="margin">Intereſt the anchoring place of the Saints.</note> to anchor their heart in peace; upon the ground and cape of this hope.</p>
                     <p>I could adviſe the godly to take that cordial counſel which Chriſt giveth his Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.
<note place="margin">Chriſts counſel convenient for the Saints.</note> 
                        <hi>Until the day break, or the ſhadows flee away, be like a young Hart upon the Mountains of Bether.</hi> That however the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120089:33"/>of Diviſions,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Diviſio.</hi>
                        </note> may eclipſe the comforts of the ſaints proſperity;
<note place="margin">The Saints intereſt a means of union.</note> yet I ſhould wiſh this Mount of conjunction might diſpel the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of their calamity in the hour of tryal.</p>
                     <p>The godly have a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of all their enemies by reaſon of this intereſt. They have the benefit of Gods power to ſupport them in ſpight of their enemies,
<note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</note> and therefore we find, that it lyes not in the hand of the wicked to ruine the godly: I preſume it is not for want of malice,
<note place="margin">The Saints intereſt boundeth the wickeds power.</note> but might. They cannot do what they would, and therefore they do what they can. It is the happineſs of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be united to God by intereſt when the wicked are divided from him by their iniquity.</p>
                     <p>As the firſt ſecureth aſsiſtance to the godly, ſo the ſecond prepareth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120089:33"/>deſtruction for the wicked.</p>
                     <p>But ſeeing it is certain, that the Lords intereſt in the Saints is the firſt ground of his ingaging for them; me thinks this ſhould fix divers particulars upon the ſaints ſpirits,
<note place="margin">Intereſt doth ſettle the Saints ſpirits in trouble.</note> worth their ſerious medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, they are not to fear their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, when they have ſuch a friend. <hi>David</hi> is not afraid of ten thouſand of the people to trouble him, if the Lord did aſsiſt him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, They muſt not look upon the Lords ſervice as a piece of difficulty. For if the Lord have an intereſt in our perſons, he wil have a finger inour practiſe. He is as careful in the time of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity to direct and help us to do good; as in the evil day to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and preſerve us from danger.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:120089:34"/>
Thirdly, They are not to look upon their enemies, as in any ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to undo them, ſeeing the Lord doth ſupport them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the wicked</note> It ſeems it is to kick againſt the pricks to fall out with the godly becauſe whatever they are to the world, they are dear and neer to God. Let them be oppoſed by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they have a God to take their part.</p>
                     <p>I remember <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 46.7. tels his enemies that he had God for his friend, and ſo he was ſtrong enough for his ſtouteſt adverſaries And this hath put life in the ſaints when almoſt mortified with the ſenſe of their ſufferings.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">Intereſt bindeth the Saints to their good behaviour.</note> This obligeth the godly to a ſingular deportment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God beſeeming his ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. As they are above the world
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:120089:34"/>in their unity with him, ſo I would have them in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of duty to him. Oh how careful ſhould they be to honour him, whoſe principle and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſe it is (by reaſon of his intereſt) to preſerve them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                           <hi>Ground,</hi> the Saints weakneſſe.</note> The ſecond ground upon which the Lord is pleaſed to give in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to his Saints in their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering condition, is their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to deal with their enemies, who are often as mighty as malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and as numerous as furious, 1 King. 20.27. <hi>Iſrael</hi> marched like a flock of Kids before the Aramites who filled the Country.</p>
                     <p>This ground of the Saints weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth move the Lord with a great deal of tenderneſs towards them,
<note place="margin">The Saints weakneſſe the object of the Lords pity &amp; ſeverity.</note> and bitterneſſe againſt their enemies, that place of <hi>Obadiah, chap.</hi> 10.11, 13, 14, 15, 16. is worth our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120089:35"/>animadverſion, and ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
                     <p>How tenderly is the Lord affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with <hi>Jacobs</hi> calamity, and how ſmartly moved againſt <hi>Eſau</hi>'s cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, <hi>For thy crueltie againſt thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jacob, ſhame ſhall cover thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off for ever; when thou ſtoodeſt on the other ſide in the day when the ſtrangers carried away his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and ſtrangers entered his gates, and caſt lots upon Jeruſalem, even thou waſt as one of them.</hi> After ſuch like direful and dreadful expoſtulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he concludes the deſtruction of all his peoples enemies, giving a ground of his ingagement againſt them.
<note place="margin">Law of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliation, <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualis red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>For as ye have drunk upon my holy Mountain, ſo ſhall the heathen drink continually.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It ſeems the Lord will ſatisfie the temporary croſſes of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, with the continued curſes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:120089:35"/>of their enemies, and that becauſe they had inſulted upon their weakneſs.</p>
                     <p>The ſtrength of the godly is without them.
<note place="margin">The Lord is the Saints ſtrength.</note> God is the ſtrength of <hi>Davids</hi> heart, and his portion for ever, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 73 26. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all their engagements they lean not upon themſelves, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though conſiderable in reſpect of competent ability, even in the ſight of their enemies.
<note place="margin">The ſaints have no confidence in the arm of fleſh.</note> 
                        <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> profeſſeth for all his numerous ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that he knew not what to do. <hi>We know not</hi> (ſayes this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Prince) <hi>what to do, but our eyes are towards thee,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.12. He will rather lean upon God for the victory and his aſſiſtance, then to diſpute with ſuch a malicious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy by the ſtrength of a puiſſant and valiant Army, a ſtronger then which was never any aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:120089:36"/>in <hi>Judah.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Note.</note> But as there is no counſel or ſtrength againſt the Lord,
<note place="margin">It is good to have the Lord to our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> ſo is there none without him. It is good fighting under the Lords colours; if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and order the battel, the victory is certain.</p>
                     <p>The Lords preſence is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of power,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> and the ſeat of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>The Lord of Hoſtes</hi> (ſaith David) <hi>is with us, the God of Jacob is our refuge; He breaketh the bow, and cutteth the ſpear, and burneth the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots with fire.</hi> And ſo we read of Saints performances in oppoſition to enemies of greateſt abilitie and ſubtilty; ſo eminently doth the Lord who is their ſtrength act in weakneſs: <hi>Not I</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.10) <hi>but the grace of God in me</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Portus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis.</note>. This Land of Reſt was in the ſight of <hi>David,</hi> when, Pſalm 125.4. he entreats Gods benevolence for the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:120089:36"/>aſſiſtance of his brethren, <hi>Do well</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to thoſe who be true and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in their hearts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Oh that this Ground might bring forth ſomething to our ſpirits in the day of our controverſies,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applica∣tion. </seg>
                        </label> making our weakneſs more viſible to us in our conflicts with our ſpiritual and temporal enemies, ſo that we might lean more upon our God, and leſs upon our ſelves,
<note place="margin">God the beſt Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies.</note> we ſhould then ſooner have our digladiations more certainly decided, and all the contention of our controverſies peaceably determined, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes we ever can;
<note place="margin">No finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. Gods help in our councels to give advice exceeding profitable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</note> we ſhould do more in diſpatching the puncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes of Sacred and Civil differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in an hour with God, then all our dayes without him.</p>
                     <p>Let him be Preſident of our Councels, and then we ſhal find him the perfecter of our purpoſes,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120089:37"/>
                        <hi>Caſt your burden upon the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>David; Pſal.</hi> 55.22. This good adviſe doth teach us the ſhorteſt way to eaſe our ſelves. <hi>Commit thy work</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 16.3.) <hi>unto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall be directed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is no thinking of any end of that buſineſs,
<note place="margin">God muſt do all our work forus, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.12.</note> wherein the Lord hath not a finger to finiſh it: and therefore in ſhort, Let the Lord be more familiar with us, and then all our matters ſhall be a great deal more eaſie for us, there ſhall be no oppoſition which can ſtand againſt us. It is a memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble incouragement which the Lord gave to noble <hi>Joſhua, Joſh.</hi> 1.5, 7. <hi>There ſhall not a man be able to withſtand thee all the dayes of thy life; as I was with Moſes, ſo will I be with thee, I will not leave thee or forſake thee, only be thou ſtrong, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120089:37"/>of a valiant courage, that thou maiſt obſerve and do according to all the Law which Moſes my ſervant commanded thee; thou ſhalt not turne away from it to the right nor to the left hand, that thou maiſt proſper whitherſoever thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe words are directed to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort belong to all of his intereſt and Authority.</note> and in him to all of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious intereſt, Piety, honour or Authority, of whatſoever magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude they are; that they may cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read their aſſured aſsiſtance in the lines of their reliance upon, and correſpondence with God. <hi>Quo docemur ita nos, demum, fore in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnabiles ſi ad preſtandum Deo fidele obſequium enitamur.</hi> Calvin ad loc.</p>
                     <p>The third Ground of the Saints aſsiſtance from the Lord,
<note place="margin">3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                           <hi>Ground,</hi> The Lords word.</note> is his word. He hath engaged his word for their aſsiſtance in any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120089:38"/>of their conflicts, whoever be their adverſaries, of whatſoever place or power.
<note place="margin">God ſecure his Saints by his word.</note> I find the Spirit giveth a large and full account of this promiſe in many Scriptures, but eſpecially in that moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.4. wherein we have aſſurances of the Lords kindneſſe in this particular ſet down almoſt in every line, but eſpecially in the 5, 6, 7, 15 and 16 verſes, <hi>Thou ſhalt not be afraid of the fear of the night, nor of the Arrow that flyeth by day, nor of the peſtilence which walketh in darkneſs, nor of the plague that deſtroyeth at noon day. A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand, but they ſhall not come neer thee. I wil be with them in trouble,</hi> I <hi>will deliver and glorifie him; with long life will</hi> I <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, and ſhew him my ſalvation.</hi> All which be more then ordinary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions to aſſure the godly of his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:120089:38"/>favourable aſsiſtance, and doing well by them in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                     <p>And if the Saints had no more but a word of Promiſe from him who is holy and true,
<note place="margin">Gods word ſufficient to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the Saints.</note> and whoſe words are more unchangeable then the heavens it were enough; but to his Promiſes we have his precepts and words of authoritie added commanding us to make our addreſſes to him for help, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call upon me, &amp;c. I wil deliver thee, &amp;c.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Saints rely upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> And <hi>David</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth he had been much with God in that eſtate, and had found ſuch refreſhment as his ſoul could wiſh, <hi>Pſal</hi> 34.7. <hi>Thou haſt known my ſoul in adverſity,</hi> ſaith he;
<note place="margin">Saints find by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Lords words true.</note> this he ſpeaks by perſonal experience, as to what he had found.</p>
                     <p>Doubtleſs <hi>David</hi> had ſuch gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious returnes, as give his ſpirit a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:120089:39"/>great deal of enlargement in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity beyond his ordinary hopes.</p>
                     <p>The Scriptures often mention three Qualifications of the Lords Promiſes to ſatisfie his ſervants in order to their aſsiſtance.
<note place="margin">Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Lords promiſes to the Saints.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt, they are <hi>full.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, they are <hi>free.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly; they are <hi>certain.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. That his Promiſes are <hi>full,</hi> is very evident, becauſe they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out without any limitation of perſons,
<note place="margin">Lords pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite.</note> places or dangers of the godly. So that it is a part of the Saints Commonwealth, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever magnitude or ſize, they are high, low, rich, poor, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever danger they fall in,
<note place="margin">Saints ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where upon Gods Word.</note> they are alike ſharers in the Promiſes. Let <hi>David go in the vally of the ſhadow of death,</hi> he is ſure of deliverance, for God is with him, and his rod and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120089:39"/>Shepherds crook ſhall comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſerve him.</p>
                     <p>This precious ſoul could not be alone in trouble, ſuch was the fulneſſe of the Lords Promiſes to him, that he had alwaies the Lords preſence with him.
<note place="margin">Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and promiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note> Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Preſence are of the ſame dimenſion, both eſſentially infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in their fulneſs.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. They are <hi>free,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                           <hi>Qualif.</hi> Free.</note> and thus they are held out to the Saints, that they may never queſtion their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment or application upon the ſenſe of their own unworthineſſe and ſo when ſuch deſires are ſent up by them, the accompliſhment of which may be as a tree of life to them,
<note place="margin">Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of promiſes to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſweet.</note> they may confidently expect a ſeaſonable return. And ſo I find <hi>David</hi> and others never queſtion, that if they call, but the Lord will anſwer to ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:120089:40"/>
Hence the godly are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident (in reſpect of the promiſes) in the night of their adverſity,
<note place="margin">The godly more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in adverſity, then the wicked in proſperity.</note> then the wicked are negligent (by reaſon of their principles) in the day of their proſperity.</p>
                     <p>The firſt hath hope in his death when the other hath no faith in his life.</p>
                     <p n="3">3
<note n="3" place="margin">
                           <hi>Qualif.</hi> Certain.</note> That the Promiſes are <hi>certain.</hi> Chriſt is the beſt interpreter of his Fathers words Heaven and earth may paſſe away, but of them there is not one jot to be changed. <hi>O Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 7.28) <hi>thou art God, and thy words are true;</hi> Hence the Saints paſs with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence through any difficulty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt of diſturbance,
<note place="margin">The pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Saints.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are certain by promiſe that they ſhall obtain if they run the race with perſeverance, which is ſet before them. They know that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120089:40"/>he who is their life, and the length of their dayes can ſupport them in oppoſition to any Antagoniſt whatſoever, according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things being cordially conſidered,
<note place="margin">An adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement in order to an improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the premiſes.</note> Gods word of promiſe ſhould take deep impreſsion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every heart, eſpecially ſuch who have experimentally found the Lord holy and faithful, who may comfortably and confidently aſſert they never ſought the Lord in vain, but that he hath ever anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above their hopes.</p>
                     <p>Oh how ſhould a ſpirit be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the feeling of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour which hath ever ſhined cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the cloudieſt ſeaſons of their extremity, when there was none to befriend but God.
<note place="margin">The Lord a loving friend in extremity.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Oh let ſuch never forget that it is the Lords cuſtom to conform
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:120089:41"/>his kindneſſe in the thick of all diſcouragement, that the gale of his goodneſſe bloweth in every ſeaſon,
<note place="margin">His mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſweet in that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> that there is no ſtorm can ſtop his affection from watering all the plantations of the Saints, that he puts counſel and comfort, in every corner befitting their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:
<note place="margin">Gen. 32.29 1 Kin. 17.4</note> he hath an Angel for <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and a Raven for <hi>Elijah.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                           <hi>Ground</hi> His glory.</note> His own glory is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ground of his engagement for his Saints.</p>
                     <p>To this Ground we have the Scripture give in great and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent teſtimony. It ſeems the Lord ſpeaks much of the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his glory,
<note place="margin">God is jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his glory.</note> that he wil not diſpenſe with its abuſe to any, <hi>I am the Lord,
<note place="margin">The Lords glory inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for his people.</note> my glory I will not give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another,</hi> Iſai. 42.8. In the Saints troubles the Lords glory is much ingaged; the Saints are alwayes
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120089:41"/>ſufferers upon his account; <hi>For thy ſake all the day long are we perſecuted,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Note</hi> Satan in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonor the Lord by his ſervants</note> Pſal.</hi> 44.22. It is worth our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that in the Saints troubles, it is not ſo much Satans deſign, to diſquiet the ſervant, as to disgrace the maſter. That putting the Saints from their patience and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance he may turne the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of their ſhipwrack and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy upon him whom they ſerve,
<note place="margin">Satan en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoreth to affront God upon his Saints ſufferings.</note> who ſhould have eſpouſed their controverſie, he having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to own them in their ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conflicts; therefore the Lord for his glory hath engaged in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to their ſtouteſt enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14, 15. He ſuffered none to do them wrong, he reproved Kings for their ſake, ſaying, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, and do my Prophets no harm.</hi> And again, <hi>He ſaved them for his name ſake,</hi> Pſal. 106.8. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:120089:42"/>
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> in his adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth plead from his glory for his peoples deliverance, often in Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, Deuteronomie; all which, with a great many more Scriptures evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences we have to aſſures that the Lord doth good to his people in point of honor.</p>
                     <p>Here it is worth obſervation,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> if the Lord doth impledg or pawne his honor for our peace in adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<note place="margin">We are to ſerve God as a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after deliverance Luke 1.74</note> we are juſtly obliged to pay the tribute of piety to him, in the day of our proſperity.</p>
                     <p>As the Lord is pleaſed to look upon us afflicted, ſo we ſhould look upon God being delivered, &amp;c. As he tendred our good, ſo muſt we his glory. It muſt not be with the beſt of Saints, as it is with the worſt of ſinnners, to turn the grace of God unto wantonneſs
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:120089:42"/>the moſt cordial kindneſs to a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal profaneneſſe.
<note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful.</note> Let us be more the Lords then our own, ſeeing he owned us when we were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
<note place="margin">Saints in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let Gods honour be as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious as it is profitable to us.</p>
                     <p>Let us not be ſo mercenary,
<note place="margin">Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor muſt be precious to us.</note> as to balance its commodity, and not its excellency. It is of greater worth then all we can have by it.</p>
                     <p>Let it therefore be our piety to pay it its due, and our ſincerity to contribute all our endeavours to the promoting of its inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</p>
                     <p>Ingratitude is the ſhame of Saints,
<note place="margin">What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude is</note> and the Seale of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
                     <p>As it is the heighth of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to rob God of his Glory, ſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:120089:43"/>it is the pureſt worſhip in the Sanctuary to advance his honor; therefore as Blaſpemy is a ſubject of the greateſt iniquity,
<note place="margin">Blaſphemy a diſhonor to God, and the object of juſtice.</note> ſo let it be the object of the greateſt ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. For as it was crueltie to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael to ſpare <hi>Amalek,</hi> ſo it is no friendſhip to God or his truth to favour their enemies.</p>
                     <p>Let us then take notice of that glory ingaged for us,
<note place="margin">Nothing to be preferred before Gods glory</note> that our zeal be impartially ingaged for it.</p>
                     <p>Fifthly,
<note place="margin">5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                           <hi>Ground</hi> Wickeds power.</note> The power of the Saints enemies, is a ground of his ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them. Many times it falls out, that the godly are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered,
<note place="margin">The Lord is the ſaints reſerve.</note> and their party worſted then it pleaſeth the Lord to ſtep into the field with a recruit.</p>
                     <p>It ſeems this hath been often Iſraels caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129.1, 2, 3.</p>
                     <p>The Church lamenteth thus, <hi>They
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:120089:43"/>have oftentimes afflicted me from my youth, may Iſrael now ſay, &amp;c. the Plowers have plowed upon my back, and made long furrowes, but they could not prevail againſt me;</hi> (mark it) <hi>for the righteous Lord hath cut the cords of the wicked.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I find here a clear confirmation of all this truth; we read in this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, that the Lord appears for his people, when hopeleſs to do any thing for themſelves, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to their enemies.</p>
                     <p>I remember in the time of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Ariſtocracy, (or Government un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Judges) they were often ſadly and ſharply put to it by their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
<note place="margin">An obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Saints trouble, and their help.</note> inſomuch that if the Lord had not pitied their miſery, they had been undone by the malignant ability of their mercileſſe adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
                     <p>But we find there recruiting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:120089:44"/>for the accompliſhment and eſtabliſhment of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in ſuch a caſe.</p>
                     <p>That religious deportment of precious <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> towards the reproaching Ribaldrie of railing <hi>Rabſhekah,</hi> is very memorable. It ſeems he troubles not himſelfe with his language or Letter,
<note place="margin">The Saints leave their enemies to God:</note> but leaves both to the Lords conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reading for his return, he ſpeaks not a word to him,
<note place="margin">Saints are often ſilent when moſt falſly traduced or accuſed; ſo was their Savior be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pilate, Luke</hi> 23.9.</note> but ſpreads his Libel before the Lord, that he might anſwer it. He knew that <hi>Aſhurs</hi> Army was to hard for him, but not for the Lord, who could quickly diſpatch them by one Commiſſion Officer; and ſo he had them routed and ruined in a night.
<note place="margin">Judgment to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Point of the Lords aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance threatens dreadfully the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded ſpirits of the Churches ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:120089:44"/>they dream not of ſuch an Auxiliary in their confident combatings with the godly; but it ſeems they are miſtaken, they find a ſtronger and more eminent Antagoniſt then they are aware; and therefore it is hard for them to kick againſt the pricks.</p>
                     <p>And this ſpeaketh well for the godly,
<note place="margin">Mercy to the godly.</note> who commonly have few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt friends, but moſt enemies, that they have a reſerve when weakeſt, to grapple with their ſtrongeſt and greateſt adverſaries.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.10</note> It is the Saints glory to confeſſe, when they are weak, then they are ſtrong, Let us therefore in all our conflicts, mind more the favour of our God, then the fury of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</p>
                     <p>Let us joyn with him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend us,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                        </label> whoſe power is dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to all that oppoſe us. Let us
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:120089:45"/>ſpeak our troubles to him, that our ſpirits may have eaſe. Let us reſt upon him, who will not fail us. Let us keep a familiar correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with God in our proſperity, that he be no ſtranger to us in the day of our calamity.
<note place="margin">Plety the Saints poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note> It is not the leaſt part of the Saints policy to gather with God, and ſcatter with the world: they can be no loſers by ſuch an exchange in the day of trouble.</p>
                     <p>He that hath the Lord for his friend, and the world for his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, he hath Piety in his right hand, and Prudence in his left.</p>
                     <p>He is looked upon as the beſt of Saints, and wiſeſt of men, whoſe troubles prove but tryals to depend upon God: and ſeeing it is the Lords practiſe to fruſtrate the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keds power, let us have heavenly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120089:45"/>affections in our greateſt diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<note place="margin">Setled ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity.</note> and never fear that enemy which the Lord cannot only out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit, but outwork.</p>
                     <p>Sixthly,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground, </seg>6</label>
                        <note place="margin">Saints preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</note> The Saints preſſures under the weight of their troubles, doth ingage the benefit of the Lords aſſiſtance and ſupport under ſuch a burden, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7. <hi>I have ſurely ſeen the trouble of my people, and I was to them as he that taketh off the yoak Hoſ.</hi> 11.4.</p>
                     <p>I remember <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 10.11.
<note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eds deluſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on,</note> ſets downe the wicked under a ſtrange deluſion, aſſerting, that the Lord did take no notice of what the Saints did ſuffer, or they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon them, <hi>He hideth his face</hi> (ſay they) <hi>he wil not ſee.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">by Satan.</note> It ſeems the devil charmeth their ſpirits to this apprehenſion, as he did the old Epicures, <hi>Deus nec curat ſui, aut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieni.</hi>
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:120089:46"/>But how ever ſuch are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deluded,
<note place="margin">The Saints perſwaſion.</note> ſuffering Saints are more graciouſly ſchooled, and know better of God, <hi>That he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth miſchief and wrong, and taketh it in his own hand,</hi> Pſal. 10.14. The godly ſhould have <hi>(duram provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am)</hi> a hard task of their troubles,
<note place="margin">To be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected of God the ſaddeſt trouble.</note> if whilſt they are afflicted by men, they ſhould be neglected by God. Such an overſight ſhould more inwardly wound them, then all their wretched enemies could out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly wrong them;
<note place="margin">What Gods favor is to Saints.</note> for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour is better then life, and his frowning is worſer then death to a gracious ſpirit; and therefore the fainting fits of our infirmity are the deſigned objects of his paternal clemency.
<note place="margin">God is tender over his Saints.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>He will not ſuffer our brudens to ſink us, whilſt the rowling of his bowels are able to ſupport us.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:120089:46"/>
Let this reſpective kindneſſe have a ſeat in our hearts which hath ſuch an hand in happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                        </label>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let not the impreſſe of worldly diſtraction more affright us to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer then the promiſed power of a heavenly refection delight us to bear.
<note place="margin">Afflictions mitigate.</note> Let Gods words more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us with the hopes of our help, then all the world unſettle us with the threats of our hurt. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think that the vapours of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs ſhould ſo ſtupidly damp us, but that the ſpirit of grace and godlineſs ſhould more religiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly prompt us to any piece of the Lords ſervice whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
                     <p>Let us conſider what we are in proſperity,
<note place="margin">The Saints are the ſame in proſperity and adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to God.</note> that the ſame we are in adverſity to our gracious God, he is in both the ſtrength of our hearts
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120089:47"/>and our portion for ever. There may be a little of our condition e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed as to us,
<note place="margin">Gods love to his ſaints unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</note> but not a grain of affection changed, as to God; the Pleiades of his continued pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, ſweetly dropping over us, ſend down the ſame efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ential influences of power in all the weakly and ſickly ſeaſons of our croſſe bearing conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p>So that there is no fear of abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to bear,
<note place="margin">Saints are carried out by a divine power in affliction.</note> whoſoever hath laid on the burden, if we lean upon him. Hence I conceive, here is ſomething here worth the exerciſe of a Saints wiſdom in the day of trouble.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">God the Saints pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor in trouble.</note> We are not to conſult the Oracle of our owne, but of the Lords ability in that eſtate; ſeeing he beareth the purſe of power, we need not fear proviſion, under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:120089:47"/>preſſure whatſoever.
<note place="margin">Saints in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements in trouble.</note> We may be more in ſpending then ſparing, in improving then retaining what is intruſted to us.</p>
                     <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">To mind our God the ſubject of our ſtrength.</note> Whilſt our burdens lye upon us, let our weakneſs warn us where our ſtrength lieth. It is one of the greateſt Characters of a worthleſs ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Stupidity in adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſigns the indignity of a ſpirit.</note> to be a ſtupid ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, to merit little, and mind no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of its ſupplies. Such a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, as it hath but little of ſenſe, and leſs of reaſon, ſo nothing of grace in its deportment.</p>
                     <p>The choice government of a troubled Saint is well drawne up in <hi>Davids</hi> words of his dependance upon God, and his aſſiſtance by him. <hi>My ſoul</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>cleaveth to the Lord, his right hand upholdeth me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſeventh Ground of the Lords ingagement for his people,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground, </seg>7</label>
                        <note place="margin">Pride of the wicked.</note>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:120089:48"/>is the pride of their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
                     <p>The Scriptures tell us, it is not ſufficient for the Saints enemies to afflict them, but to inſult over them. And thus as the godly are put upon all the ſenſes of ſorrow, ſo the Lord puts himſelf upon all the ſervice of their ſuccour and ſupply, in not only oppoſing the power but the pride of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</p>
                     <p>Of this we have large teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from the Lords word,
<note place="margin">The ſaints know the pride of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> and the Saints experience; but that there is an inſulting ſpirit predomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the wicked over the Saints, is ſeen often in the ſufferings of the godly under it.
<note place="margin">The Saints complaine of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity for caſe.</note> I have heard <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in his Pſalmes bemoaning this piece of his injuries by the wicked, beſeeching the Lord to eaſe him of ſuch an indignity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.2. <hi>Let
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:120089:48"/>not mine enemies rejoice over me, &amp;c.</hi> and elſewhere often he entreateth the ſame favor. I take notice of the Churches voice, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Rejoice not againſt me, O my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This kind of iniquity is a bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of that curſed impurity which naturally in the wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth the diſgrace of the godly.
<note place="margin">What this pride is.</note> For it is ſo with that cruel root of bitterneſs,
<note place="margin">Pride of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies how it groweth.</note> that it never thriveth in any ſoul, but when it is wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the contempt of the Saints, which renders their caſe the more conſiderable,
<note place="margin">Saints con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſuffer.</note> in that they are objects of their enemies ſcorn. It is the Saints humility to ſubmit to their croſs; but the wickeds pride and pravity to trample them under it.</p>
                     <p>God doth not take it well at the wickeds hand, that they ſhould
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:120089:49"/>adde affliction to the afflicted; he ſeems to reſent it,
<note place="margin">God wil be avenged of his Saints enemies.</note> when he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to make them repent it, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they medled with his people, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 10.12. he promiſeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Aſhurs</hi> pride, after the perfection of <hi>Zions</hi> peace. He tels us,
<note place="margin">The Saints enemies have their time of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation.</note> that <hi>he had not done with Aſhur, when he had made an end with Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; He muſt lift up the curſed Ephah from Iſrael,
<note place="margin">Zach. 5.10, 11</note> and place it in the Land of Shinar.</hi> He will burn the broom which beat his children.</p>
                     <p>Me thinks (theſe things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) it is dangerous medling for the devil or the wicked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and his children. I have obſerved from the Scriptures he vvill have none ſo much as to laugh at their calamity,
<note place="margin">The Lord will have his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren beaten by none but by himſelf</note> but at their peril of mourning in the day of their proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:120089:49"/>
He looks upon it as a juſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel againſt the vvicked, that they are ſo forvvard to ſet him againſt his people, and to bring faggots to the fire of his fury. And are ſo ready to run upon them in the day of his diſpleaſure.</p>
                     <p>Thus we may ſee what the Lord is in reference to his people.
<note place="margin">How God dealeth with his people, and for them.</note> He hath love in his anger, and anger in his love, yet ſo vvell ſoddered for their ſafety, as that he acteth the firſt, for the correction of themſelves, and the ſecond for the deſtruction of their enemies.
<note place="margin">God muſt bridle the wickeds malice.</note> If the Lords povver did not check the vvickeds pride, the vvorld vvould ſoon be too hot for the godly: How happy then are the Saints,
<note place="margin">The Saints happineſſe in trouble wherein it ſtands.</note> vvho hath one that can lodg them in deſpight of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and protect them in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to all their pride.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:120089:50"/>
Let it therefore be the Saints wiſdom to value the Lords pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er above the wickeds pride.
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applica∣tion. </seg>
                        </label> If this laſt afflict them; let the firſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them. It is the Saints com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort as they are occaſionally obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to injuries, ſo they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntially attended with the beſt of remedies. The Saints have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes their Phyſitian by them, whilſt they are on this ſide of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
<note place="margin">Davids de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the ſaints.</note> Their poſition of <hi>Davids</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent, aſſures them of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent. If they can but win their ſpirits to the unity of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, there is no queſtion of the commodity of his aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                     <p>Eighthly,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground, </seg>8</label>
                        <note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keds ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</note> and laſtly, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable malice of the Saints ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, is an eminent reaſon of the Lords ingagement for them, to oppoſe their fury. This the Lord
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:120089:50"/>hath comfortably concluded in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his ſervants.
<note place="margin">Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> 
                        <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou haſt a perpetual hatred, and haſt put the children of Iſrael to flight, by the force of the ſword in the time of their calamity,
<note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> when their iniquity had an end, I will lay their Cities waſte, &amp;c.</hi> Ezek. 35.4, 5.</p>
                     <p>As the wickeds malice argue their miſchief, ſo its continuance threatneth their ruine.
<note place="margin">Malice the bane of the wicked.</note> The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked would do a great deal better by themſelves, if they dealt kindly by the godly.</p>
                     <p>It hath been obſerved, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice with continuance,
<note place="margin">What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice is.</note> is but the devil in diſguiſe, who loves ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be abroad in the hearts of the wicked, then at home in hell.</p>
                     <p>Therefore to ſupplant his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, and to prevent his cruelty, are eminent acts of the Lords
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:120089:51"/>kindneſſe in favour of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                     <p>I have alwayes obſerved that the Lord is pleaſed by the power of his grace,
<note place="margin">An obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Gods favor to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> to make the Saints wiſer then the vvicked, and ſtronger then the devil. So that hovvever both may hate them, yet neither can undo them.</p>
                     <p>They may be implacable in their malice, but incapable in their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to do them any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harm.</p>
                     <p>The heat of their hatred may blacken their beauty,
<note place="margin">Malicecan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not undo the godly.</note> but let Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his inſtruments do what they can, the Saints are ſtill comely as the Tents of <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> and the Curtains of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is not the ſtaining of the Saints Colours, but the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Saints comforts,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120089:51"/>that is their ſorrow.
<note place="margin">The Saints more affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with eclipſing of their graces, then loſs of their good</note> The brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things of malice may deface the firſt, but the gates of hell are not able to obſtruct the ſecond. For as the Saints have hope in their death, ſo they are bleſſed with the continued comforts of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al life, let the devil and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked do what they can.</p>
                     <p>The godly were in a piteous condition,
<note place="margin">Satan would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do the Saints if God did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent him.</note> if they had no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment then what Satan would beſtow; he would ſtarve them to his ſervice, and kill them in it; he would feed them with the bread of affliction to prepare them for deſtruction. But it is the Saints happineſſe, they are not upon his allowance. They have bread, whereof he knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
<note place="margin">Saints are not ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> the ſecrets of their mercy is ſhut up from him, and they are not ſtraitned of their provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:120089:52"/>even in the worſt of times. It is not Satans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice that can mince their mace.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou haſt prepared a table for me</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 23.5.) <hi>in the ſight of my adverſaries.</hi> The Lord wil let Satan and the wicked know he keeps his ſervants well, that they may conclude, there is nothing wanting to them that fear him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34.9.</p>
                     <p>It is the ſweetneſs of the Lords Spirit,
<note place="margin">The Lords kindneſſe comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſharpeſt ſeaſon.</note> the ſharper the wicked hate his Saints, the dearer he loves them, and the better they fare; <hi>For I am with thee to ſave thee, and deliver thee,</hi> ſaith the Lord to <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Jer.</hi> 15.20.</p>
                     <p>So me thinks Satan and his Clyents are but fools for all their fury;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Concluſ.</hi> The folly of Satan &amp; his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> they do but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend the godly by their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:120089:52"/>thus melting the Lords affection in a warmer fervency to his Saints,
<note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed defeat their owne deſign.</note> and ſo becoming guilty of the death of their own deſign; they ſhew what they can do, but not what they would.</p>
                     <p>It ſeemes they have not ſo much rope in their <hi>poſſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cannot execute their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt the godly.</note> as they have ſcope in their <hi>velle.</hi> Dogs may ſhew their teeth although they durſt not bite.</p>
                     <p>Here me thinks it is no loſs of time to pauſe a little admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that mercy which compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Saints.
<note place="margin">Saints fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor great.</note> 
                        <hi>How great is thy goodneſſe which thou haſt laid up for them that fear, and done to them that truſt in thee before the ſons of men,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 31.19.</p>
                     <p>We ſee amongſt all the ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of Satans ſubtilty, he is
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120089:53"/>not more reſtrained in any,
<note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cannot but as they have.</note> then in this of the wickeds malice, that thoſe his emiſſaries cannot hurt, as they hate; the Lord ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving chained up their ferity with the cord of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion;
<note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eds week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> ſo that there is no ſtirring for Satan or his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants beyond the reach of their line, let them ſtruggle what they can.</p>
                     <p>Oh then,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                        </label> how ſhould the Saints love their mighty God, whoſe power is their preſervative againſt ſuch an evil,
<note place="margin">Saints are not given up to the wicked.</note> that he will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his Saints to be ſacrifices to the will of their enemies; they may hunger for their deſtruction, but ſtarve before they obtain it. It is not malice can catch the prey, when mercy prevents it. <hi>David</hi> is here cruelly hunted by <hi>Saul,</hi> but graciouſly ſupported by God. It
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:120089:53"/>is not his malice can murder him, or his plotting that can ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize him; for the Lord was with <hi>David,</hi> whither ſoever he went.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:54"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:54"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>BOWELS of MERCIE</hi> BREATHING FOR THE SAINTS IN DANGER: OR SACRED SYMPATHY UNSEALED.</p>
                  <p>BY <hi>ALEXANDER PRINGLE,</hi> A Worthleſs Servant to Chriſt in the Work of his Goſpel.</p>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<bibl>
                        <hi>Col. 3.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Maxey</hi> for <hi>Wil. Weekley</hi> at <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>J. Rothwell</hi> at the Fountain in Cheapſide, 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:55"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:55"/>
                  <head>LECTORI INTEGERRIMO.</head>
                  <p>INter Multifaria, blate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis hujuſce ſeculi <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, nulla tam perfrictae frontis videtur nequitia; quam eſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta in Evangelicae veritatis <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Impudens <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Qua dum univerſa <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> dogmata conſpurcare ſtudeat <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, cruentos quoſdam è ſuis ſpelaeis excitat Lupos <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſceleratiſſsimo quorum Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio,
<pb facs="tcp:120089:56"/>Jurgia non modo, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> refertiſſsima ſed &amp; Zizania in Domini vinea vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulentiſſima operoſe diſſeminat. Sic ut mediantibus hiſce, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Satanicae hujuſce praxeos nefarii, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; non tantum ſunt <hi>Socinianae,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellites, <hi>Pelagianaeque</hi> vafri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae verſipelles vaferrimi, aut enthuſiaſtici <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticae</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſed &amp; alii quam plurimi purae-putae indignantis ignaviae ſoboles aſtutiſſima <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſimulata quorum pietas du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicata
<pb facs="tcp:120089:56"/>evadit iniquitas; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſque aurigatio ruſtica aut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina quaedam civica, aptius multo convenit quam ratione ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocinante de crypticis fidei my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriis <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> diſſerere, aut ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae paginae digeſtis <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, imponere, competit; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> verum iſti <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuas ineptias ac dilirantis cerebri diliria effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire geſtiunt nullumque non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent lapidem quo jure, quave in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juria, ut evangelii ſacris ejuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſervis fideliſſimis <hi>Nigro Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone</hi> ſligmata inurerent. Hinc <hi>illae Lachimae!</hi> quantum langueſcit Pietas,
<pb facs="tcp:120089:57"/>marceſcit puritas, gliſcit iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ingruit aequitas, quam eſt Domini vinea ſpinoſa, dumis, vepretisque referta, Luporum ſpelunca, maleſuadae partim ignorantiae, omnigenae propemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum dementiae deformata in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinamentis; quanta eſt non modo errorum colluvies, ſed et convitiornm ubique congeries, quam eſt effrons blaſphaemiarum aenea facies adeo ut tranſmari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae illud heterodoxias <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> auribus identidem intonat, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſchiſmaticum, aut haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Anglo-eſt, aut Scoto-Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannicum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pudet haec opprobria dici,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:120089:57"/>Verum hiſce ex animo ſerio ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duloque penſatis <hi>(Integerrime Lector)</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> hanc ſequentem, boni Conſule; ejuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> lucubrationibus favere Perge, qui eſt Theologicae veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſalut iferae aeternae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuae (in Chriſto) beatitudinis</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Summa Obſervantia Studioſiſſimus,</hi> AL. PRINGLAEUS.</signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Harvegiae <date>5 Id. Feb. 1657.</date>
                        </hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:58"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:58"/>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>BOWELS of MERCIE,</hi> BREATHING FOR THE SAINTS IN DANGER.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PSAL. 125.4.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Do well, O Lord, unto thoſe that be good, and true in their hearts.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N This Supplicatory Addreſs, we have the breathing of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gracious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, wiſhing good to the godly, entreating the Lord earneſtly for them; that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120089:59"/>it may go well with them in the day of trouble.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> It is eaſie to find out the actings of this ſpirit (in Scripture) upon, and in the hearts of all the godly whilſt they are carried forth with the ſtreames of heavenly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſpiritual tenderneſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the bleeding and ſuffering condition of their precious bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
                  <p>We find <hi>Eſth.</hi> 3.1, 2.
<note place="margin">Mordecai</note> modeſt <hi>Mordecai</hi> was extremely moved when he was informed, that the Jewes (the Lords peculiar people ſhould be utterly ruined.</p>
                  <p>The ſpirit of honeſt <hi>Uriah</hi> could not be perſwaded to reſt and ſleep at home in peace,
<note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riab.</note> when the Ark and <hi>Iſrael were abroad in danger, By thy life,</hi> (ſaith he to <hi>David</hi>) <hi>and by the life of thy ſoul I will not do this this thing,</hi> 2 Sam. 11.11. It ſeems
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120089:59"/>his ſpirit could not be brought to delight in any ſuch refreſhment, vvhilſt it vvent hardly vvith the Lords people.</p>
                  <p>I read <hi>Nehem:</hi> 1.4.
<note place="margin">Nehemiah</note> that gracious <hi>Nehemiah</hi> takes no pleaſure at Court vvhen he heard that poor <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> vvas lying plundred, burned, and broken dovvn in the Country; he tells us, hovv much he vvas af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected vvith her trouble, <hi>When I heard theſe words, I ſate down and wept and mourned certain dayes, and I faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and prayed before the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame melting ſpirit vve find in zealous <hi>Daniel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Notandum eſt cum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpres eſſet ſomniorum Daniel non tamen fuiſſe elatum vel confidentia vel ſuperbia</hi> Cal. ad loc.</note> accounting little of his perſonal preferment, vvithout a ſeaſonable aſſurance of <hi>Iſraels</hi> National inlargement, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.3. <hi>I turned my face unto the Lord God, and ſought him by prayer and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, with faſting, ſackcloth and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes.</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:120089:60"/>By all vvhich and many more of his expreſſions vve may obſerve he vvas more humbled, and tenderly afflicted vvith the Church her calamity, then in the leaſt exalted or affected with the illuſtrious eminency of his perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal dignity.</p>
                  <p>I conceive the ſame tenderneſſe of ſpirit which vve find in <hi>Mordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai, Uriah, Nehemiah, Daniel</hi> and others, did predominate in <hi>David</hi> vvhen he prayed ſo affectionately, <hi>Do well, O Lord, unto thoſe that be good and true in their hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe vvords are digeſted in one of thoſe Pſalmes vvhich are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a diſtinguiſhing Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter,
<note place="margin">Text de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Songs of Degrees.</hi> This Inſcription is prefixed to fourteen Pſalmes more of the ſame denomination,
<note place="margin">Difference of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout he ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this Pſalm.</note> and hath coſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, both Jewiſh and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120089:60"/>Chriſtian, more then ordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition; all of them paſſing their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> upon it, but with little or no ſatisfaction in it.</p>
                  <p>I remember <hi>Calvin</hi> tells us of the Jewiſh Doctors, that they only divine, and not certainly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine or agree about it. <hi>Hic Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; quindecim ſequentes vocantur graduum, qua ratione, non convenit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam inter Hebreos Doctores, quidam fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt quindecim fuiſſe gradus ad partem templi uvas deſtinatam; quum infra ſubſiſterent mulieres,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Quindecini Pſalmi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur,</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>graduum, vel Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quibus va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae ſunt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piniones alii à gradibus templi, alii ab aſcenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſeu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentione vocis dictos volunt, alii genus melo diae fic dictum, alii Pſalmos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſionum,</hi> i. e. <hi>reditus Judeorum a Babilone in Judeam ut</hi> Beza. <hi>Alii volunt eſſe tonos modu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis, ut</hi> Calvinus. <hi>Mollerus Lyrani ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tontiam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur de gradibus cleri la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotum.</hi> Par. adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. in Pſa. 120</note> ſed frivola eſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinatio &amp; ſcimus quantum licentiae in rebus obſcuris ſibi permittant Judaei ad quidivis fingendum.</hi> Cal. in Pſal. 120.</p>
                  <p>And for Chriſtian Expoſitors both ancient and modern, they conclude nothing certain; they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo conjecture, that theſe Degrees are ſpoken of certain places, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain orders of perſons, certain
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120089:61"/>Deſcants, and Tones of Voices; wherein, by whom, and how thoſe Pſalmes have been ſung.</p>
                  <p>Concerning this punctilio of the Title of this, and thoſe other fourteen Pſalmes, we need not make much inquiry, we may ſafely joyn with Learned <hi>Paraeus,</hi> and conclude, <hi>In re tam obſcura &amp; non magni momenti liberum cuique judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium;</hi> That is, in a thing of ſo great obſcurity, and ſo ſmall uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, we may leave every man to abound in their owne ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>For my part, I have ever thought the time better ſpent in improving Scripture Truths, then in ſearching out the fruitleſſe pedegree of Scripture titles.</p>
                  <p>The ſubject matter of the words make up a conſiderable part of this Pſalme. It ſeemes it is <hi>Davids</hi> deſign
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120089:61"/>(for I look upon him as the Author of this Song) to cheer up and conſolidate the ſpirits of the godly three wayes,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By promiſes from God, ver. 1, 2, 3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By Prayer to God, ver. 4.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By Prophecying againſt the wicked.</p>
                  <p>The words I have choſen, ſeem to fill up the middle rank of this order: for as judicious <hi>Calvin</hi> well obſerveth upon the words, after that <hi>David</hi> had given aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to all the godly, of their eſtabliſhment and refreſhment in affliction, ver. 1, 2, 3. In order to their farther Confirmation, he prays for the accompliſhment of the ſame promiſed aſſurance, <hi>Quamquam propheta certo piis omnibus pollicitus fuerat opportunum auxilium ſe tamen ad precationem convertit.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Calv. ad loe.</note>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:120089:62"/>And he tells us, that this addreſs of <hi>David</hi> was not in vain; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our Faith in the Promiſes may ſupport us in reſpect of God, yet our fleſh doth weaken us in reſpect of our ſelves, that there is need of Prayer to ſtrengthen us in attendance of the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Promiſes. <hi>Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra quia etſi nos ſuſtentet fides quia tamen interea vacillant carnis noſtra ſenſus, preces miſcenda ſunt ad confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem. Calv. ad loc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So much for the words of my Text, as they ſtand in order to their Contexts. If we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in themſelves, we have them here formed to our hand in the Model of an addreſs to him, who had formerly given aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance it ſhould go well with the godly in their ſuffering condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The rod of the wicked
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120089:62"/>(ſaith he) ſhall not lye upon the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the lot of the righteous, v. 3.
<note place="margin">The fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my text.</note> And thus my Context cometh to hand in ſeaſon, as a ſutable ſubject exciting the Saints this day to an interceſſion for their brethren in that eſtate.</p>
                  <p>The words be naturally digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in two material members:
<note place="margin">Text di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is a Supplication, <hi>Do well, O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Deſignation of certain ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect perſons, for whom the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs is tendred, <hi>viz. ſuch who are good and upright in their heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It ſeems <hi>David</hi> puts up a requeſt to God,
<note place="margin">For whom David prays.</note> but it is for ſuch as be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eminent Characters of Piety and Sincerity: <hi>Neque tantum ſimpliciter rogat ut bonos benigne tratet Deus, ſed bonitatem quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> definit quis manat ex ſincero affectum. Calv. ad loc.</hi> I apprehend <hi>David</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120089:63"/>here the faithful of the land (as he phraſeth the godly, Pſ.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Note.</hi> Gracious Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates car ful of the godly.</note> 101.6.) he is very careful of the party that they may be happy in a ſweet correſpondence with God in the day of trouble. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he intercedes in thoſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Benefac Jehova:</hi> So <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, Tremelius, Do good, O Lord.</hi> To do good, is an act <hi>(primario)</hi> Firſtly, from <hi>Jehova,</hi> as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all Beeing and Goodneſs:
<note place="margin">Operari ſequitur eſſe.</note> he is that <hi>Primum bonum &amp; ſummum in eſſe:</hi> He is that primitive Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Good in being, and ſo from himſelf doing good in operation. All inferior agents are ſubordinate to his moderation in all their tranſactions. Hence <hi>(in recta ferre cauſalitatis)</hi> in the right caſe of cauſality,
<note place="margin">Means productive as influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by God.</note> all means, of whatſoever magnitude or qualification, are onely productive, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:120089:63"/>as they are influenced by him to do any good, and ſo the Lord as he is the firſt, ſo he is the beſt, and choiceſt of Chymiſts,
<note place="margin">God the beſt Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</note> to quinteſſentiate the good of his people, from the moſt malignant materials.
<note place="margin">Saints reſt in God for aſſiſtance.</note> And therefore <hi>David</hi> in this addreſs doth trouble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf no farther to call in the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary ſuccurrence of any ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate inſtrument whatſoever to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend the Saints in trouble, but here goeth confidently to the Throne of Grace,
<note place="margin">Saints know where to go in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Heb. 4.16.</note> for the Lords benevolence to his people in the time of need. I preſume <hi>David</hi> was no ſtranger in heaven, and therefore knew with whom to intercede for the Saints on earth. He had often experience, that the God of Iſrael was the Lord of Hoſts,
<note place="margin">David ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with God by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> and the Saints ſureſt and ſweeteſt friend, and ever ſooneſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120089:64"/>to be found for counſel, comfort, and all accommodation, in the evil day.</p>
                  <p>Me thinks <hi>Davids</hi> practiſe ſhould be the Saints patern in their addreſſes to heaven for themſelves or others.
<note place="margin">Davids practiſe ſhould be a copy to us to go to God.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>They muſt not ſeek to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
<note place="margin">Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</note> but the firſt hand, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements in the day of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; they are to eye the God, and not the Men of Iſrael; Mercy before Means; the Fountain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Streams; Gods Favour, before humane Fidelity or Ability whatſoever.
<note place="margin">David a good man and a good Magiſtrate</note> This is the method of <hi>David,</hi> one of the beſt of men, (a man according to Gods own heart) and one of the choiceſt of Magiſtrates that ever did bear principality or charge over the Lords people: And ſo much for his Supplication.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:120089:64"/>
His Deſignation is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for the good in the plural.
<note place="margin">The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs.</note> It ſeems the party for whom this addreſs is made, are ſet apart by <hi>David</hi> as ſingular for their qualification.</p>
                  <p>I conceive it is not neceſſary I ſhould make any fixed diſcourſe of thoſe Characteriſtical impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by which they are illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and deſigned in my Text;
<note place="margin">Animad. before.</note> onely we take notice, that this party is precious both in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and <hi>Davids</hi> account.</p>
                  <p>In themſelves they are ſet down to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and thoſe be Characters of ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent worth,
<note place="margin">The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons praid for are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, &amp; of a choice qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that they alwayes denominate the ſubject excellent, and above the ordinary ſize or ſtature of Profeſſors.</p>
                  <p>To be good,
<note place="margin">To be good, what</note> is to be of God by participation.</p>
                  <p>To be upright,
<note place="margin">To be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, what</note> is to to be of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120089:65"/>his word by qualification.</p>
                  <p>And to be both in heart,
<note place="margin">To be both good and upright, what it is.</note> doth ſigne the truth of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Theſe be the marks of Honor, and letters of Religion, ingraven and written upon thoſe perſons which render them ſo precious in the eyes of <hi>David,</hi> that their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment gives him incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to make a preſentment of their condition before the Lord.</p>
                  <p>A gracious people are very dear to a godly Magiſtrate: <hi>David</hi> is tenderly affected, that ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſouls ſhould be afflicted;
<note place="margin">David ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieth the happineſs of the Lords people.</note> and therefore (as their Prince and Prophet) he is willing to do his utmoſt for them, that it may go proſperouſly with them; by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this ſerious Addreſs to God, that he would befriend them, in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120089:65"/>oppoſition to all of their enemies whatſoever. <hi>Do well, O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſubſtance of <hi>Davids</hi> words may be the comfortable ſeminary of ſeverall ſweet Concluſions.
<note place="margin">The fulnes of this text</note> But for the preſent, I ſhall briefly take notice of two onely.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.
<note n="2" place="margin">Concluſ. from the words.</note> That there is a ſpecial regard to be had of ſuch who be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and or godly, whilſt they are in danger.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We are to deal earneſtly with God, to befriend them in that eſtate.</p>
                  <p>Both which Concluſions ſeem to be the rule of <hi>Davids</hi> practiſe, and the ſubject of his prayer in this place.</p>
                  <p>The party for which <hi>David</hi> pleadeth, is not of a trivial tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
<note place="margin">Who are thoſe who are truly godly.</note> but of the deepeſt ingrain of godlineſs, being clothed with the choiceſt impreſſes of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120089:66"/>holineſs: <hi>True and upright in their heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>It is worth our obſervation as we paſs along,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Note.</hi> Of Davids Spirit.</note> that it was one of the eminent ingredients of <hi>Davids</hi> accompliſhment, to have his heart affected with, and his eye direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the honour and happineſs of the Saints: <hi>My eyes are upon the faithful of the land,</hi> Pſal. 101.6. <hi>All my delight is in them,</hi> Pſal. 16.3. Thus ſetting an excellent copy to all of his intereſt, both for Piety, and Authority to value the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Doct. or the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſ. proved</note> that there is a ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to be had of the godly in danger.</p>
                  <p>This is a matter of ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial concernment amongſt the Saints, that I finde it not onely as a duty eminently recommended to them, but religiouſly improved
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120089:66"/>by them, as a ſervice ſutable to their intereſt; <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> Pſal. 122.6. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them that are in bonds, as if ye were bound with them, and them that are afflicted, as though ye were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted in the body,</hi> Heb. 13.3. <hi>Weep with them that weep,</hi> Rom. 12.15.</p>
                  <p>Hence is effectuate that tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit in the godly over their brethren; ſo compaſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſympathiſing with their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and indempnities, as if they were perſonally ſtricken with the ſenſe of their ſufferings,
<note place="margin">Doctrine ſhortly cleared fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, in the Saints moving them to brotherly tenderneſs.</note> and the preſſure of their burthens.</p>
                  <p>That there is ſomewhat more then ordinary amongſt the Saints, which ſtirreth their bowels to ſuch a benevolence, may be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate from theſe Motives.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive. </seg>1</label>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10. Eph. 4.6.</note> From their mutual relation to God, that they are all of one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120089:67"/>Family,
<note place="margin">Mar. 23.9. Eph. 5.23, 26. Eph. 5.26. Acts 2.38. Rom. 8.17</note> of one Father, having the ſame Saviour, the ſame San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier, the ſame intereſt in the Promiſes and Priviledges, as heirs of the Kingdom of Grace and Glory.</p>
                  <p>This relation is none of the leaſt,
<note place="margin">Saints are of the ſame relation.</note> if not the firſt ingagement upon the Spirits of Saints, to take to heart the caſe of their brethrens threatned, or inflicted calamity; they being all Members of the ſame Body, they become all part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſame malady, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive. </seg>2</label> their Diſpenſations from God; theſe alſo being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.16. Eph. 4.7. 1 Pet. 2: 9, 10. Saints are of the ſame diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of grace 1 Cor. 1.30</note> that they live under the droppings of the ſame benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; being all of them, <hi>a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Generation, a royall Prieſthood, a holy Nation, a people ſet at liberty;</hi> being all of them <hi>called, juſtified,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120089:67"/>and ſanctified,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.3 Gal. 2.20 Eph. 4.5, 6</note> having the ſame life and livelyhood of Faith and Love, with the hope of Salvation, doth ſo influence the ſouls of the Saints with a more then ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, both in proſperity and adverſity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Galat. 6.2. Phil. 2.4.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive. </seg>3</label>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 4.5 Gal. 5.13 Rev. 19.10 Gal. 1.10 Acts 14.22 Saints are of the ſame miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Luke 1.24 Mat. 24.45 Rev. 2.10 Hence the Saints are put to it. 2 Cor. 4.8 But gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Job 23.10 Iam. 1.3, 4 The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> their mutual Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that they are all of one Oeconomy, fellow-ſervants to the ſame Lord, having their work laid out in oppoſition to more then a Legion of Adverſaries, which want neither craft or cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty to compaſs their ruine, doth ingage their ſpirits to an affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Sympathy of one anothers condition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.4.</p>
                  <p>Hence the truth of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine may determine its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">uſe </seg>1</label> By obligation to binde the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120089:68"/>Saints with all the cords of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian kindneſs to a fraternal feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their mutual calamity. It is a convincing Argument of the Saints accompliſhment, if they be affected with their brethrens trouble;
<note place="margin">Saints known by their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs.</note> ſuch a tenderneſs doth ſpeak them like themſelves. It is a more then ordinary carnal exorbitancy to be without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. As it ſealeth the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, ſo it ſigneth the Cruelty of an unreformed ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a gracious heart,
<note place="margin">How be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend the ſaints.</note> then to befriend the godly: for as it is an act of our obedience to God; ſo it cleareth our correſpondence with him.</p>
                  <p>Therefore let the ſaints adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be of eminent efficacy to oblige our prayers for their advantage in the evil day.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                     </label>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:120089:68"/>
2. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">uſe </seg>2</label> By Reprehenſion of ſuch who are not onely of a ſeared Principle,
<note place="margin">Of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</note> but of a ſelfiſh Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, in prejudice of the godly; who are no more touched with a ſenſe of their ſufferings, then are ſuch who have no intereſt in them.</p>
                  <p>In order to the juſt rebuke of this Antichriſtian Apathy in ſuch ſtupid Stoicks,
<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for their apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Saints troubles.</note> I ſhall offer theſe Conſiderations:</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Confid. </seg>1</label> they live in the world without a love to Chriſt; their non-commiſeration of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, witneſs them cold to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; ſeeing it is not ſo much the ſervants, as the maſter in them, which ſuffereth in the world; <hi>Non tam vos quam Deum in vobis perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur,</hi> ſayes <hi>Martia.</hi> It is not ſo much you, as God in you which they perſecute. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<note place="margin">Acts 9.4</note> 
                     <hi>Why
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120089:69"/>perſecuteſt thou me?
<note place="margin">Chriſt a ſufferer in his Saints.</note> Me (inquit) non meos,</hi> Auguſt. de Sanct. 14. My ſelf and not mine: Chriſt is pleaſed to call his Saints diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies his own, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41, 42, 43. <hi>I was hungry, and ye gave me no meat; and thirſty, and ye gave me no drink. I was a ſtranger, and ye took me not in; I was naked, and ye clothed me not, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is worth our Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Chriſt was not onely once willing to be a ſufferer for his ſervants, but as yet conſtantly is contented to be afflicted in them, <hi>Patitur in vobis Deus,</hi> ſayes <hi>Martial</hi> Epiſt. 2. It may be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox in Nature to hear of a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering God, (a Deity under infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity) yet this is nothing admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to be aſſured that Chriſt, who is <hi>God manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi> the Head of the Body his Church,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120089:69"/>to be contemned in his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:
<note place="margin">Chriſt takes part with his ſaints.</note> 
                     <hi>Contemnitur Chriſtus dum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnitur membrum Chriſti,</hi> Auguſt. in Pſal. 50. Chriſt and his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are ſharers of the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. There is nothing which doth more diſcover enmity to God, then antipathy to the godly.
<note place="margin">God and his people alike hated</note> 
                     <hi>Inſectantur &amp; oderunt ſervos Dei &amp; in eis Deum.</hi> Salvian de Provid. lib. 8.</p>
                  <p>It is eaſie to finde out how that ſpirit is affected to the Maſter, who hath no pity of his afflicted ſervants.</p>
                  <p>It is not likely that Chriſt is much reſpected,
<note place="margin">Animad.</note> when ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saints are altogether neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And therefore me thinks it is no injury to conclude againſt the love of thoſe to Chriſt, who hath,
<note place="margin">There is no love to God where there is none to his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note> or ſheweth none to his members,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120089:70"/>1 Joh. 4.20, 21. I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the head is not precious to ſuch, who care not what become of the body.</p>
                  <p>Let this be a warning to hearts hardened againſt the Saints cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that they keep a cold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt. <hi>Chriſtus lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur, Chriſtus patitur, quia in mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris Chriſti Chriſtus eſt. Loquitur caput pro corpore, &amp; corpus in capite.</hi> Aug. in Pſal. 30.</p>
                  <p>There is ſuch a myſtical Unity betwixt Chriſt and his Members,
<note place="margin">No corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with Chriſt without his members.</note> that there is no correſpondence with the one, without reſpect to the other: they ſuffer, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the ſame injury; <hi>Tanto vos affectu amare dignatur, ut quod nos patimur, ipſe ſe pati teſtatur.</hi> Aug. Hom. 15. Such is Chriſts affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to us, that he witneſſeth his affliction for us. Therefore,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:120089:70"/>
If this day I might be eſteemed worthy to counſel you,
<note place="margin">Ezhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all the ſaints.</note> I would ſeriouſly deſire you, conſider the troubles of your brethren, as if they were your own; their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as your indemnity: Such a care, as it becometh your intereſt in them, ſo (let me tell you) ye are concerned in their ſafety: <hi>All things come alike to all men,</hi> ſayes <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> Eccles. 9.2. <hi>Cuivis poteſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidere, quod cuiquam poteſt; ſcito omnem conditionem verſatilem eſſe &amp; quod in illum incurrit in te quoque, incurrere poteſt.</hi> P. Syr. apud Senec.
<note place="margin">Troubles common to al the ſaints.</note> That which befalleth one, may befall another. And it is worth obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation (ſaith he) That every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is changeable, and the lot of one may fall in the lap of another.</p>
                  <p>And this is a Truth beyond Contradiction,
<note place="margin">An adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement to all.</note> That there is no
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120089:71"/>people or perſon whatſoever that hath ſuch armour of proof,
<note place="margin">Animad.</note> as is affliction-free.
<note place="margin">Tum tua res agitur, &amp;c.</note> It is the great Councel of Providence, which paſſeth Decree of the Saints trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and determineth preciſely of its individual objects; the Saints muſt be no chooſers, but bearers of their burthens,
<note place="margin">Our own caſe muſt warn us.</note> 
                     <hi>Ille ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ego cras</hi> (ſayes ancient <hi>Bernard</hi>) He to day, and I to morrow.</p>
                  <p>Therefore let this be a word in ſeaſon,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                     </label> to ſuch who would ſeal their love to Chriſt, to ſhew more then ever their cordial affection to his ſuffering Saints.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>2</label> ſuch whatever they are to the world,
<note place="margin">Such are dead who are not tender of the godlies caſe or ſufferings.</note> yet they are dead as to God. As they are not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Saints danger: ſo they are not quickened with the Saints life. If they were of their ſpirit, they would act like their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120089:71"/>being; <hi>operari ſequitur eſſe:</hi> opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or action, is the natural flux of eſſence: as things are in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo they Act. <hi>Hereby we know, that we are tranſlated from death to life, becauſe we love the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.14.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing which ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more the life of grace in our ſelves,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Note.</hi> A mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip without compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſenſe.</note> then to commiſerate the mortal ingagements of the godly. It is but a kinde of a mechanick Memberſhip, which ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not with the caſe and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of the perſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<note place="margin">Ex Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> a wooden leg natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally is of no feeling, or moving, as a ſilver noſe is of no ſmelling, and a withered hand of no hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<note place="margin">Dead members in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for ſhew only.</note> and yet thoſe are in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more for ſhew then uſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether ſenſleſs of its pain or pleaſure. So theſe members
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120089:72"/>are dead in themſelves,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> which are paſt feeling the dangers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. They are rotten as to the body, which doth not compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate its ſufferings. <hi>Membra putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da &amp; mortua ſenſum non habent, tales ſunt Chriſtiani qui de alienis malis &amp; afflictionibus non dolent.</hi> Auguſt. in Pſal. 130. Hom. 15. As rotten and dead members (ſayes he) have no ſenſe; ſuch are Chiſtians who for the evils and calamity of others have no ſorrow.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is no wonder, the wicked are much of <hi>Gallius</hi> ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Acts 19 The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of the ſaints con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> careleſs of the Saints calamity, they having never taſted of their comforts. They live not the Saints life, and ſo are ſenſleſs of the Saints lot; they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrangers to the ſanctimony of their conditions, and therefore to the ſeverity of their afflictions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:120089:72"/>
Therefore me thinks this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration may prove ſerviceable,
<note place="margin">Strong arguments to tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> as an effectual incentive to all the godly, that as they have an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent intereſt in the things of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; ſo to owne the tranſient troubles of their brethren here upon earth.</p>
                  <p>Thus as they are not of the world, they will diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from it; as they are the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs of Glory, they will convince the world they are the precious children of the Spirit of Grace. Therefore</p>
                  <p>I ſhall humbly beſeech all the godly,
<note place="margin">Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all the ſaints</note> in this juncture of <hi>Jacobs</hi> trouble, to witneſs their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by their practice; what they are in the graces of their life,
<note place="margin">To wreſtle with God.</note> by the greatneſs of their labour this day with the Lord; Let it be known to the enemy, that there
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120089:73"/>be Chariots and Horſemen in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> and that the practice of the Saints by prayer, is of greater power in heaven,
<note place="margin">The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> then all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies or Armies whatſoever, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon Sea or Land.</p>
                  <p>Let it not be ſaid,
<note place="margin">We muſt look upon Chriſts members &amp; intereſt in trouble.</note> that we want a life to breathe for the refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts Members, leſt he take it ill at our hands. Who knoweth, but he hath ſeparated us from the ſadneſs of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that we might be ſuiters for their ſafety? It is good for them, that we may be honoured to have a ſubordinate hand in their happineſs.</p>
                  <p>Let their ingagement put a more then ordinary ingagement upon our ſpirits:
<note place="margin">The ſaints danger an argument of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion.</note> Let it be a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of publick evidence, that we live not onely to our ſelves, but to our brethren.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:120089:73"/>
It ſhall be a glorious victory which is purchaſed by prayer; it ſhall be a triumph of the Lords contriving, a day of the Lords deliverance, and an eminent evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Lords benevolence to our <hi>Britiſh Jeruſalem;</hi> it ſhall be worth our pains, worth our prayers; it will determine our intereſt in God, by our prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him in behalf of his Saints.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>3</label>
                     <note place="margin">No zeal to God, where there is no love to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note> as ſuch are not affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a ſenſe of the Saints miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſo they are not warmed with a zeal to the Lords glory. It is very certain, the ſame ſpirit which is troubled with the one, is melted with the other.
<note place="margin">Animad.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is ſuch a ſtrict commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion betwixt the Lord and his ſervants,
<note place="margin">The ſaints neglect is the Lords diſhonor.</note> that he not only accounts their injury, but neglects, as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:120089:74"/>to his glory: and therefore where there is no ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for his Saints; he looks for none or little reſpect to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                  <p>I could heartily wiſh, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoul conſidered ſeriouſly a few things of that correſpondence kept betwixt God and his ſervants in extremity. The thoughts of which, would influence their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to a ſympathy of their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it becometh the Lords and our intereſt in them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>1</label> It ſeems the Saints are more the Lords then their own; and therefore nothing can befal them wherein his Glory is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>2</label>
                     <note place="margin">Satan the ſaints and the Lords enemy.</note> The Lord and his people have the ſame common adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who endeavoureth the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of the one, as the ruine
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:120089:74"/>of the other; and in oppoſition to him, the Lord equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth for both.</p>
                  <p>The Saints are ſufferers for God,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>3</label>
                     <note place="margin">Saints ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer upon the Lords account.</note> and therefore it is not to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, when they are afflicted by the wicked, that they are neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him: But the more they are perſecuted for him, the more they are owned by him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared to him, by all the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate ingagements of love and honour.</p>
                  <p n="4">4.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>4</label>
                     <note place="margin">Saints hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines what it is to God</note> We muſt take notice that the Lords honour conſiſteth much in the ſaints happineſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch as befriend their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, are promoters of his glory.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>5</label> As there is nothing ſo dear to God as his glory
<note n="*" place="margin">Eſa. 42.8 Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the ſupply of he ſaints.</note>; ſo there is nothing can ſooner ingage it, then the ſaints neceſſity: for as his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120089:75"/>honour is precious to him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Deity; ſo are his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants wants in reſpect of his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency.</p>
                  <p n="6">6.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>6</label>
                     <note place="margin">God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to the ſaints re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to himſelf.</note> It hath ever been the Lords cuſtome, to ballance the ſaints fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with his own; alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging himſelf a debtor to both, in order to a comfortable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital: If a cup of cold water is not to be forgotten, how will greater courteſies be remembred? We need not think we ſhall be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers by the godly, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to their neceſſity,
<note place="margin">There is gain in doing the ſaints good</note> if the Lord be our pay-maſter: for he is never ſhort, but alwayes exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in liberality our expectation or deſire.</p>
                  <p n="7">7.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>7</label> It is an eminent act of the ſaints wiſdom, to mingle mercy to their brethren, with duty to God; and thus thinking they cannot
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:120089:75"/>ſerve God better,
<note place="margin">It is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God to befriend the ſaints.</note> then in befriend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the godly.</p>
                  <p>It is one of the groſſeſt parts of the wickeds folly, that they imagine a correſpondence with God, but not with his people; being ſtrongly poſſeſt, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they may be in arrear to him, yet they are in nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>btors to them. Thus they often offer to God, with ſtrange fire, the Idol of their own conception.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Seeing there is nothing more conſiderable in the eye of God,
<note place="margin">To be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor upon the ſaints account.</note> then to favour his ſervants; Let us ever be ſenſible of the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Lords honour, in the afflictions of the godly. It was not ſo much the routing of the Hoſt of Iſrael,
<note place="margin">The cauſe of Elies death:</note> or the ruine of his children, as the captivity of the Ark, and the blood of the Saints, which was the cauſe of <hi>Elies</hi> death.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:120089:76"/>He was more afflicted with the injury of Gods glory, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the ſorrow of all his domeſtick indempnity; it was Gods diſhonor, and not his own loſs, which broke his heart.</p>
                  <p>The wife of <hi>Phineas</hi> minds more <hi>Iſraels</hi> glory,
<note place="margin">and of his daughters.</note> then her husbands death; the taking of the Ark, then the travelling of her birth; the departing of glory from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then of life from her ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Oh how tender is a gracious ſpirit of the glory of God. It is the ground of the Saints ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the wicked: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhould be of eminent effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy to draw a ſtrong party, even all of its intereſt to their aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is eaſie to conclude this Conſideration,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                     </label> that they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of another intereſt, then
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:120089:76"/>that of the Saints, who are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their ſufferings.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>4</label>
                     <note place="margin">Doggiſh anpidity hindreth tenderneſs of ſpirit.</note> ſuch doggiſh ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, <hi>Caninae aequanimitatis ſtupor;</hi> As it ſmells nothing of Religion, ſo it croſſeth all antural affection. It is below the excellency of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not to compaſſionate the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury of nature.</p>
                  <p>There be none but ſuch who are appointed to ruine themſelves, which do not pity the ruine of others: <hi>Soli filii irae iram non ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt nec triſtantur in triſtibus.</hi> Bern. Ep. 256. They are the children of wrath (ſayes he) who are not ſenſible of wrath,
<note place="margin">A danger not to be touched with the ſaints con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> and are not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected when their brethren are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</p>
                  <p>It ſigneth not onely a worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, but a ſpirit of immanity, not to be troubled with anothers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, <hi>Quis</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>illam ubi nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:120089:77"/>animum tangit affectas ſtuporem immanem quo nullo prorſus erigatur neque excitetur affectum non enim quia durum aliquid inde rectum aut quia ſtupidum ideo ſanum.</hi> Auguſt. lib. 14. de Civit. cap. 10.</p>
                  <p>Who ſaith, he can ſpeak any thing of that Apathy,
<note place="margin">Apathy of inexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble injury to our ſelves &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> which ſpoileth the minde of affection, and covereth it with a ſtupid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, ſo that there is nothing can ſtir it, is it therefore a thing right, becauſe hard? or ſound, becauſe ſtupid?</p>
                  <p>Let this give a ſhort,
<note place="margin">An adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement of tryal of ſpirits.</note> but a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Advertiſement to ſuch, to try their condition, who are more in charity with themſelves, then any elſe; who love rather to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne accompliſhment, then to give incouragement to others; that whatever <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they paſs upon themſelves, they may
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120089:77"/>conſider again, and they ſhall finde, that this their ſenſleſs apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the ſtate of others, ſigneth them to ſhare more of the worſt of ſinners, then of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Saints; and more of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, then Men, who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together careleſs, what become of their Neighbours. We are not onely by Nature rational, but ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial: <hi>Homo ſum humani, nihil &amp; me alienum puto.</hi> Terent.
<note place="margin">The want of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, doth deſign us of a more then bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ſpirit.</note> The very heathen could ſpeak in order to their kinde, and the befriending of it: how much more ſuch, who have learned in the School of Chriſt, <hi>to bear one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and to be tenderly affectionate towards one another, as becometh bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I heartily wiſh, this ſecret counſel might be ſerviceable to ſome, who have not onely caſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:120089:78"/>off the bond of all ſpiritual frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the godly;
<note place="margin">Spirits warned of their <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> but alſo of natural humanity with others: ſo that they take no more notice of their danger, then if they were not concerned in their ſafety. They minde nothing of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of others, ſo it go well with themſelves: They will neither be at the coſt of prayers for them, or of incouragements to them in their troubled condition; ſuch is the Genius of thoſe ſtupid Stoicks, who think they were made for none but themſelves; whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are elſe void of compaſſion, as their hearts of holineſs, or their ends of future happineſs.</p>
                  <p>It would make a ſoul tremble to think,
<note place="margin">A fearful expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuch who are not tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</note> what pity they can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect for themſelves, who will ſhew none to others; what love they can look for from God, who
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:120089:78"/>hath none to the brethren; who hath neither hearts or tongues to befriend them.</p>
                  <p>It is a rule which admits of no exception, That judgement mercileſs, belong to them who ſhew no mercy.</p>
                  <p>Therefore me thinks it were the wiſdome of ſuch,
<note place="margin">Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuch.</note> to take war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that ſuch an apathy of ſpirit is nothing elſe, but a mortal Meſſenger of their haſtening miſery.</p>
                  <p>It is good for us to deal with others, as we would have a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God to deal by us: if we would have favour, we muſt be favourable; if pity, muſt be piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; if tenderneſs,
<note place="margin">brotherly tenderneſs ſpeaks us the Lords children.</note> we muſt be troubled with the afflictions of others. There is nothing which ſpeak us more the Lords children, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bear the image of this grace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:120089:79"/>
But to conclude this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                     </label> let the thoughts of the godlies ſufferings ſo influence our ſpirits, that by the very character of Sympathy, we may be ſigned to be of their intereſt.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe a ſenſleſs apathy doth better become unnatural a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortives, then the children of a heavenly extraction; Let us im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our paſſions to ſweeten the afflictions of the Lords people in this juncture of their need, and pray with this ſame gracious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in my Text, <hi>Do well, O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo much we have thought fit to preſent for the reprehenſion of thoſe ſullen ſelfiſh apathy, who are altogether careleſs of the ſad eſtate of the godly in their comfortleſs dangers.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Laſt Uſe</hi> of caution.</note> if the Saints muſt be regarded by us, when dangerouſly
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120089:79"/>ingaged for us,
<note place="margin">To beware of iniquity ſeeing it is the cauſe of our own and others calamity.</note> in oppoſition to any cruel enemy whatſoever; let not our iniquity prove their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage.</p>
                  <p>It is ſuppoſed by many, (and that not without reaſon) that our domeſtick iniquity may indanger them abroad; that our perſonal private ſins, may make them pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſufferers; <hi>Cum aliorum peccata Deus in aliis videtur ulciſci.</hi> Auguſt. in Joſ. quaeſt. 8. whilſt God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the ſins of one upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
                  <p>It is ordinary in Surgery to ſear the Neck, for a Reuhme in the Eyes; to open a vein in the Arm, for a predominant Humour in the Body.
<note place="margin">Joſ. 7.1, 2, 3.</note> We read of one wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>Achan,</hi> which troubled the whole Camp of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ſin, became a national ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:120089:80"/>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.16.17.</note> Thouſands of <hi>Davids</hi> ſubjects were ſufferers for <hi>Davids</hi> ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Son muſt dye for his Fathers offence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 20.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Abimelechs</hi> family is plagued for his perſonal overſight.</p>
                  <p>The firſt-born in <hi>Egypt</hi> muſt be killed, becauſe <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Others puniſhed for ſins which they had not committed</note> It ſhould be tedious to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the courſe and conſequence of ſin, in its practice and diverſity of its puniſhment, as to the perſon offending, or others. <hi>De anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate quia uſurparit unus, in eos qui nec fecerant nec factum noverant vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta proceſsit. Auguſt. contra Julian. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>Such who have neither known or done any thing to ſins practice, yet may be ſharply afflicted with the curſe of its puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>It is in the Lords diſpoſal,
<note place="margin">Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</note> to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:120089:80"/>puniſh as he pleaſeth; he can change, or chuſe the object of the Rod, without the leaſt injuſtice.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it muſt be our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant care to pleaſe God, and our filial fear to offend him, upon the account of our brethren, leſt our ſins make them ſufferers, and ſo they pay the debt which they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver took on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">It is our happineſs to be holy.</note> It is one of the greateſt courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies we can do to our ſelves or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Lords people, to be holy and harmleſs, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract no diſeaſe which muſt be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon them; making them the Patients, although we are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents.</p>
                  <p>I humbly conceive then, we are to make peace with God for our ſelves, if ever we think to be uſeful to our brethren: God will firſt be in unity with us, before
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120089:81"/>he will be entreated by us. God heareth not ſinners, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.31. We ſhall make bad Orators for others, who cannot ſpeak a word with confidence for our ſelves:
<note place="margin">No in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion without reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                     <hi>Cum diſplicet is qui intercedit irati animus ad deteriora provocatur:</hi> It is not for us to intercede, unleſs we be in favour with God, our prayers are but provocations to him.</p>
                  <p>Therefore let our firſt work be Reconciliation for our ſelves, and the next interceſſion for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>It is the ſaddeſt of injuries which cometh by ſin;
<note place="margin">Note.</note> for the fault of one may prove the plague of many: <hi>Unius facinus plurium peſtis. Salvian de Provid. lib.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>There is none more unhappy amongſt the creatures,
<note place="margin">Sin like Satan and the Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice.</note> then thoſe who kill at diſtance; as doth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan by ſin, and the Cockatrice by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:120089:81"/>ſight: nothing can cure the ſting of their poiſon, but the death of the Patient.</p>
                  <p>It is a part of that hurt the Saints receive from their Neighbours,
<note place="margin">Saints ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers by the wicked</note> that they can wrong them by their wickedneſs at the greateſt diſtance. When the Lord maketh inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſin, he hunts at home; if he finde it in the whole Body, he can puniſh any member.</p>
                  <p>Oh that this were conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<note place="margin">A receipt to enre.</note> we might take a ſhorter courſe to cure our calamity by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting blood of our wickedneſs for the health of the body.</p>
                  <p>It is a Maxime in Policy; <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius pereat unus quam unitas:</hi> Better that one, then the whole ſociety periſh.</p>
                  <p>I have ever obſerved Piety to be the beſt ſecurity, both for our ſelves and others,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:120089:82"/>
And therefore I conceive it a matter of eminent concernment,
<note place="margin">A word to all.</note> to be near to God; for then we ſhall not onely be ſerviceable to our ſelves, but profitable to the godly.</p>
                  <p>It is like,
<note place="margin">Saints are the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers with God.</note> when we live at Court, we may prove Favourites, and ſo be ſerviceable to our friends. To walk with God, is an act of duty to him, and certainly of great utility our ſelves and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. Such a deportment doth not onely befriend our perſonal advantage, but all the Iſrael of God.</p>
                  <p>Now then to conclude this fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Conſideration, of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the Saints in their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition. If ever we intend to have our ſpirits helpful to our Brethren, they muſt be helpful. We muſt not think to preſerve
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:120089:82"/>them by our Addreſſes to God, when by our ſins we provoke him.</p>
                  <p>There is no prevailing with God for good,
<note place="margin">Saints are fit ſuitors when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in ſpirit.</note> till we ceaſe to do evil; and then it ſhall be brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tenderneſs indeed of the firſt magnitude, to remove their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, by renewing of our ſpirits. Thus preſerving their proſperity, by the purity of our prayers, and purging that from our ſelves, whoſe peſtilential contagion may be the bane of others.</p>
                  <p>We know the right ſide cannot be well, when there is a Pleurifie in the left; when the heart is ſick, the head is heavy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non eſt enim pondus verae virtutis inſenſibilitas cordis, quia &amp; valde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſana per ſtuporem membra ſunt, quia &amp; inciſa ſentire dolorem non poſſunt. Greg-Mor. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:120089:83"/>
Where inſenſibility of the heart is, there is no weight of true ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; becauſe the members are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthfully ſtupified, and being cut, they feel no pain.</p>
                  <p>As if the Moraliſt ſhould have ſaid,
<note place="margin">Analogie of the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical &amp; the myſtical body.</note> When there is no feeling in the heart, then the members are dead, and <hi>vice verſâ.</hi> When the members are mortified, the heart is ſenſleſs.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is eaſie to unriddle his conception, that there muſt not onely be a ſymmetry of parts, but a Goſpel-ſympathy of hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Lords people in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  <p>I could heartily wiſh,
<note place="margin">Objection ſolved.</note> one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were removed by the force of this Doctrine, before we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
                  <p>It is the common Calumny of the wicked,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> who have leſs of God
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:120089:83"/>then corruption, That there is no ſuch binding relation upon the ſpirit of any, obliging them to a ſtrict obſervance, or ſympathiſing correſpondence of, and with the ſuffering condition of the Saints.</p>
                  <p>This piece of arrogance hath no little efficacy to break Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an communion, and to make our ſpirits anſwer with <hi>Cain, Am I my brothers keeper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore to cut the root of this poyſonable Coloquintida, we ſhal ſhortly preſent two things:</p>
                  <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                     </label> As there is nothing more perniciouſly deſtructive to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſociety, then ſuch a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: ſo all the Laws of Religion and Reaſon do forbid its pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; <hi>Anima ut in toto corpore tota eſt, &amp; in qualibet ejus parte, ideo cum ſit aliquid in exigua particula corporis quod non ſentiat anima; illa tamen
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120089:84"/>tota ſentit, quia totam non latet. Auguſt. de Trinit. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. As the Soul is in all and every part of the Body, and there is no part of the Body inſenſible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which is demonſtrate, the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy not onely of the Natural, but of the Myſtical Body, in its life, motion, affection, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual compaſſion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                     </label> It is a Dictate of the Deity, tranſcribed by <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 6.2. <hi>That we bear one anothers burthen, and ſo fulfil the law of Chriſt,</hi> which ſpeaks nothing more, then a fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal correſpondence of the Saints ſpirits in the time of trouble, that as the Saints have common bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in Chriſt, ſo they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon burthen for him. Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame Body, are of the ſame tenderneſs and feeling, if they be not dead; and if ſuch,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120089:84"/>they are not of Chriſts Body, or inlived by him: <hi>Qui non dolet cum pungitur &amp; vellicatur pro putrido &amp; mortuo membro habetur. Auguſt. Hom.</hi> 18. Such a member (ſaith he) which is not pained when pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, is deſervedly eſteemed rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and dead.</p>
                  <p>By which we are certified, there is none of Chriſts Body, but ſuch who are touched with a ſympathy of his Members.</p>
                  <p>Therefore let us ſavingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<note place="margin">Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> as there is no duty of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter utility;
<note place="margin">Saints communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</note> ſo there is none of greater authority to be improved amongſt Profeſſors of the ſame Goſpel, and its intereſt, then this is.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum patiuntur membra corporis ejuſdem quomodo alia membra, licet ſuperiora non compatiuntur membris u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius corporis laborantibus. Ambroſ-Epiſt.</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:120089:85"/>22. When members of the ſame Body are ſuffers, how can the one be without the ſympathy of anothers trouble?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum membra quaedam ſunt in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatione quadam in pace, &amp; iſtos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſtat eorum tribulatio, &amp; illos pax illorum conſolatur. Auguſt. in Pſa.</hi> 30.</p>
                  <p>There is ſuch a communion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt members of the ſame Body, that they are ſad and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, as it goeth well or evil with them, in their ſaddeſt and moſt peaceable times. It ſeems it is their practice, <hi>to mourn with them who mourn, and rejoyce with them who rejoyce.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ever obſerved,
<note place="margin">No ſuch communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as that of the Saints.</note> that there is no ſuch communion kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt any, as amongſt the Saints, both in adverſity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity; but eſpecially in the evil day, the time of common
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:120089:85"/>danger; then they all cry with <hi>David, Do well, O Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much for the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.
<note place="margin">The firſt Doct. fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond conſiderable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> ſuggeſted to us by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Prayer, cometh to hand, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the Lord is to be intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to befriend his people in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.
<note place="margin">Proved.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This, it ſeems, is <hi>Davids</hi> Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; let it be our Patern: Let us take ſome pains this day for the Saints profit: <hi>Eſa.</hi> 62.7. <hi>Give him no reſt, till he repair and ſet up Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> &amp;c. It is not for Saints to be ſilent, whilſt their Brethren are ſuffering: We are to pray for <hi>Zions</hi> proſperity, if we love our own: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6. <hi>They ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper that love thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lord is pleaſed to make
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120089:86"/>the peace of his people,
<note place="margin">The Saints prayers profitable.</note> the return of their prayers, that he may not onely ingage them, but all of their Brethren, in the duty for ſuch a purchaſe; and ſo it is eaſie to finde out, how zealouſly and often the ſpirits of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath been ingaged for their Brethrens ſecurity in the day of calamity; <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſayes <hi>Samuel</hi>) <hi>it hath pleaſed the Lord to make you his people, God forbid that I ſhould ſin in reſting to pray for you,</hi> 1 Sam. 12.24. It ſeems <hi>Samuel</hi> lookt upon it as an act of iniquity, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the Lords people of the Benefit of his Prayers. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, his addreſſes for them to God, might prevent their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</p>
                  <p>How importunate is <hi>Abraham</hi> for the Saints in <hi>Sodom!</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 18.25, 26.27.</note> How zealous is <hi>Elias</hi> for all the Iſrael
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:120089:86"/>of God! <hi>Nehemiah, Jeremiah,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> for the children of the Captivity! It is no marvel to reade thoſe gracious Orators ſo compaſſionately earneſt for the obtainment of their end, ſeeing the proſperity and intereſt of the Lords people, hath been ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently dear unto them, that they have joyntly ſtriven to advance it at their utmoſt peril.</p>
                  <p>I confeſs there be very ſolid Arguments and Grounds for the Saints ingagement in behalf of their Brethren,
<note place="margin">Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for he Saints prayers.</note> in the day of trouble: as</p>
                  <p>Firſt, in reſpect of God;
<note place="margin">Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. Exod. 19.5, 6.</note> they are owned by him as his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, his peculiar treaſure, though all the earth be his, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5.</p>
                  <p>As there is none like himſelf amongſt the gods; ſo there is none like them amongſt the Nations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:120089:87"/>
They are not onely near, but invaluablely dear unto him: <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the ſight of the Lord, are the death of his Saints,</hi> Pſal. 116. The Saints harm, toucheth his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. <hi>He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of my eye.</hi> God is highly concerned, both in the Saints injuries and favour; he taketh both their enemies and friends as his own;
<note place="margin">God looks upon the Saints e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies &amp; friends.</note> aſſuring us, if we make account to keep in with him, we muſt befriend his ſervants: ſo that there is no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponding with him, without praying for them in the day of trouble. He looks upon thoſe to be moſt cordial to himſelf, who are moſt compaſſionate to his Saints.</p>
                  <p>I conceive the godlies intereſt in God, is no ordinary argument to their Brethren, of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:120089:87"/>to him upon their account. They may truly apprehend their welcome with God,
<note place="margin">God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth prayers for his Saints.</note> who come about ſuch buſineſs to him.</p>
                  <p>The Lord likes ſuch ſuitors who come often before him, as Interpreters onely of his Saints Neceſſities.</p>
                  <p>Hence it comes to paſs,
<note place="margin">Saints prayers prevail.</note> we ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome finde any returned from the Throne of Grace, without a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Whilſt <hi>Daniel</hi> was praying and opening the caſe of his peoples calamity,
<note place="margin">Dan. 9.20, 21.</note> there is a Meſſenger diſpatched to eaſe his ſpirit, with the glad tidings of a timely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance to the Church: ſo he had his queſtion reſolved, and his minde ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>Prayers in behalf of the Saints,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> is a part of that ſweet communion which we entertain with God;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120089:88"/>for as long as we have tongues to ſpeak,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 34.15.</note> he hath an ear to hear: And I finde, that the godly have taken this courſe of correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with him in behalf of their Brethren.</p>
                  <p>Let us then in the firſt place conclude,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>1</label> That it is the greateſt part of the Saints happineſs on this ſide of heaven, to be in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with God. For thus in their greateſt extremity, they are not onely precious to God, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to all of his intereſt; and they are not onely the objects of Mercy, but the ſubjects of the Saints Prayer, <hi>Do well, O Lord, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>2</label> in our ſerious Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to God,
<note place="margin">Not to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God without our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note> let us ever be mindful of his ſervants, if they be in danger: Let us not come before him without them; ſo we
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120089:88"/>ſhall ſpeed the better: and let us take notice, when we pray for the Saints, we but befriend our ſelves; the more we endeavor their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, the more we promote our own: The Lord hath ingaged our Addreſſes for them upon our own account; and it is not to be queſtioned, but he will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our kindneſs.</p>
                  <p>Let therefore this pregnant ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Saints Unity with God,
<note place="margin">The Saints union with God, muſt incourage our proyers for them.</note> beſpeak our deportment in Prayer, that it be ſuch as pleaſe God, and profit the Saints: for they are precious to him; let them be ſuch to us: Let us not forget their neceſſities, whilſt we are earneſt for our own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies.</p>
                  <p>The Lord wil have our Prayers to be the Proxies of our Spirits, and to ſign our qualification with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120089:89"/>ſo that all their Dialect muſt be ſweetened with Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>I humbly confeſs, it is harder to love another, then our ſelves; but the Saints are taught to love both alike, that our hearts may ſeal their ſincerity to God and his intereſt.</p>
                  <p>I cannot but take notice,
<note place="margin">Animad.</note> before the diſpatch of this Argument, how unkinde they are to God, who minde not his afflicted ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; whoſe caſe is as comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as danger can make it. I do apprehend ſuch, as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs themſelves guilty of want of unity with God; ſo of intereſt in his Members.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall cordially deſire all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, who ſeem to be reſpective to God, They would be ſuch to his precious ſervants: Let Gods
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:120089:89"/>love upon their hearts, warm them to a conſtant communion with his Saints; and ſo fixing it as a Monument of their kindneſs to him, never to be forgot.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall farther preſume to adde a word to the premiſes:</p>
                  <p>That the Lord takes ſuch for enemies to himſelf,
<note place="margin">A word of inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> who do not poſitively befriend his Saints; and ſo any may conclude, in what relation they ſtand to God; by what of reſpect they carry to them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Arg.</hi>
                     </note> the godly are to be preſented to God in their dangers or troubles in reſpect of the Nation: to which they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</p>
                  <p>The godly of a Nation,
<note place="margin">The gedly the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the nation.</note> as they are the party of the greateſt worth as to God; ſo they are of the greateſt advantage to their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:120089:90"/>They are not like fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Weeds, which trouble the ground, but ſuch a Seed as make the ſoyl the better; a Garden of the Lords dreſſing; a Vineyard of his own watering; a Vine of his own planting; and a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry of his own bleſsing:
<note place="margin">They are profitable in many reſpects to a nation.</note> and their proſperity is of ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity to the Countrey wherein they converſe, that they are gueſts which make the houſe the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<note n="1" place="margin">In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ornament.</note> in reſpect of Ornament: the godly are a Nations glory; they put an honour upon it, which naturally it hath not in it.</p>
                  <p>There is a diſtinguiſhing Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,
<note place="margin">The Church thenations glory.</note> written upon <hi>Zion,</hi> Pſal. 48.2. which is not to be read up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Mountains of the earth. It is not onely the Beauty of the Nations, but eminent by its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120089:90"/>being <hi>the City of the great King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is no wonder that <hi>Eſay</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, <hi>The Mountain of the Lords Houſe to overtop the hills;</hi> ſeeing it is a habitation of Holineſs, and the Sanctuary of the Lords Reſt.</p>
                  <p>I would have people to look upon the godly with other eyes, then upon the world. There is as great difference betwixt them and the children of this world, as is betwixt the precious and the vile, the heaven above, and the earth below.</p>
                  <p>We muſt think it is not for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<note place="margin">Saints are eminently owned.</note> the Spirit doth ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently own them with a choice in the world, as if they were not of it.</p>
                  <p>I have often liſtened, to hear the voice of God in his Word, ſpeaking to them as <hi>his People,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 33.12.</note> his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:120089:91"/>Inheritance,
<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>4.1. 1 Cor. 6.19 Rom. 8.16 Gal. 3.26. Can. 5.2, 3 Eph. 5.23. 1 Co. 12.12. Bſa. 40 11. Luk. 12.32 Job. 10.3. Eze 34 12 Ezra 5.11.</note> his Tabernacle, his Temple, his Children, the Spouſe of Chriſt, his Love, his Dove, his Undefiled, his Body, his Members, his Flock, his Sheep, his Servants.</hi> All which moſt eminent Titles of Love &amp; Honor, do more then ordinary demonſtrate in what account they are with God, and how to be lookt upon by the world: But let the Sons and Daughters of Nature think what they pleaſe of the Saints; they ſhould be very contemptible with God, if they wanted their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                  <p>The world without the godly,
<note place="margin">What the world is without the Saints.</note> is like the firmament without ſtars; or the Elementary Region, without the light of the Sun.
<note place="margin">The Saints the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack of the Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> It ſhould not onely be darkened by privation of their perſons (the Zodiack of the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs) but for want of their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120089:91"/>practice, which do ſhine like Lights in the world.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not ſtand to put honor upon the Saints, to honor the world: Let this world only take notice from a little, That the ſame is obliged in point of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, to wiſh well to the godly; and if their prayers were profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, they have reaſon to pour them out upon their neceſsity, ſeeing they are their Ornament in reſpect of God; they ſhould befriend them upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
                  <p>But all this is in vain to the wicked;
<note place="margin">Preocau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</note> they have other thoughts of the godly;
<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doe lowly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of the godly.</note> they put a lower eſteem upon them, and upon what is theirs; their Perſons, Principles, and Practice, are but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vvith them: they eſteem not them vvorth their
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:120089:92"/>ſociety, much leſs of aſſiſtance; but leaſt of all to be named in the day of eminency and ornament amongſt them; they ſcorn to hold any communion of reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or honour with them; and therefore to perſwade ſuch a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, were to beat the Air; or <hi>are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam arare</hi>) there is no ſpeaking of a correſpondence betwixt God and Belial, in any ſeaſon, either of proſperity or adverſity.</p>
                  <p>Let us therefore turn from them who are more apt to adde affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the afflicted,
<note place="margin">Apoſtroph or a word to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> then to ſweeten the Saints condition, and to prevent their diſtraction in the evil day.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall humbly beſeech the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore,
<note place="margin">Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> who are of the ſame intereſt and unity with their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that for <hi>Zions</hi> ſake they would wreſtle with their God.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120089:92"/>Let the lives of the Saints be as precious to them, as to the Lord who bought them. Let us call ſtrongly for the people of the Lord and the Ark of his ſtrength (the Goſpel and its inlargements) Let there be nothing ſo near our hearts,
<note place="margin">Blood of Saints of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt price. A dear commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> as the blood of Saints, which is a thing of the greateſt price in heaven or earth: Let the honor of the Lords people, and their continued ſafety, be a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of our happineſs, that <hi>it may not be ſpoken in Gath, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the ſtreets of Askelon,</hi> that the Lords Worthies, and the work in their hand, ſhould not onely be worſted, but ſhamefully deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the enemies of the Lord, and his people, but that the Lord would do his great Work, that <hi>all the world may know there is a God who ruleth in Jacob, and a King in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:120089:93"/>Iſrael;</hi> and that it may be ſet home upon the ſpirit of the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that <hi>their God is not like ours, even themſelves being judges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">It is a ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Saints to have their party re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached.</note> let it be preſented to God, the condition of our Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sadneſs, if it ſhould go hard with the godly in this dangerous ingagement; if the godly be the Nations glory, what an eclipſe of that honour ſhould overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow the ſurface of the City of God? How would the enemies of God blaſpheme, and they of no Religion cloud it with their Calumnies,
<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keds rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> telling us, with more then impudent arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, That our intereſt in heaven is but ordinary, or none at all, ſeeing the Saints have ſhared with the common hardſhip of the wicked.</p>
                  <p>Let us deal earneſtly with our
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:120089:93"/>God in behalf of the Ornament of the Nation, to which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, ſeeing it is laid in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the faithful of the land, that choſen Generation, whoſe ſafety is the Nations honour, and their own happineſs.</p>
                  <p>Let this be preſented to God, that we may receive a comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able anſwer in behalf of our Brethren. It ſeems they ſtand or fall not to themſelves, but to all of their Brethren and Compatriots:
<note place="margin">Remember the godly are the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions glory</note> They are their Ornament, and to loſe this with an enemy, is a double af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, it is to yield to an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which we would not part with to our deareſt friends.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is to make our ſelves a ſcorn to them who thirſt our diſgrace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:120089:94"/>
I ſhall proceed no farther in this; onely leave you to be thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Argument, to act your Spirits to a farther ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with God, for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Correſpondence with thoſe qualified perſons in my Text, thoſe true and upright in heart, whoſe ſpirit with all its accompliſhments, is more the Lords, then their own.</p>
                  <p>Let thoſe precious ones be obliged to your prayers for their ſecurity, and the Nation to them, and their intereſt for its remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able eminency: for they are the Nations Ornament.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, they are not onely the Nations Glory, but the Pledges of its peace and ſecurity.</p>
                  <p>It ſhould go hard with the wicked, if they had no favour for the godly; they ſhould not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:120089:94"/>onely fall ſhort of mercy, but of all opportunities of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                  <p>It is remarkable in the Hiſtory of the Deluge,
<note place="margin">Noahs preaching and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Ark, defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the flood.</note> That all the time <hi>Noah</hi> was building the Ark, he was warning the world of their danger: But whilſt he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring this great Veſſel, the world was in no fear of drowning: <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family muſt be ſhipt, before the world be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; he muſt be ſhut in the Ark, before the waters break out upon the earth; when he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, the world is ruined. It feems all the Inhabitants of the earth are undone, when <hi>Noah</hi> is gone.</p>
                  <p>God promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſave five Cities for ten righteous perſons.
<note place="margin">God will have the wicked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to the Saint.</note> God is graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have the world beholding
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:120089:95"/>to the godly, upon a religious account, that they may be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that Piety is of great price with God, and of ſingular effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the Saints, to befriend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others. <hi>Paul</hi> had the lives of all them who are ſhipt with him, preſented to him for ſalvation; that all might take notice of <hi>Paul</hi> to be the Lords fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, and an eminent Courtier in Heaven, although now <hi>Nero</hi>'s Priſoner upon earth.</p>
                  <p>Many times,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> the godly are much miſtaken by their Brethren;
<note place="margin">Saints miſtaken.</note> and it is no wonder; for Satan their great Adverſary,
<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the godly to deform them.</note> hath not onely a minde to malign them, but a black Art to diſguiſe them under ſeveral ſhapes. He is not onely a dexterous deceiver in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but a malicious traducer in the perſon of others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:120089:95"/>
Let this give a running Caveat to Saints,
<note place="margin">A Caveat to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> not onely to conſider the ſubtile cruelty of Satan, but the ſacred integrity of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſervants (although ſtrangers) with a great deal of Chriſtian can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and tenderneſs of ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>But if the ſafety of the Nation lean ſo much upon the Saints. I truly think we need no other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to befriend them, but the aſſurance of our own, in their happineſs and ſafety.</p>
                  <p>There is an obſervation of the Spirit. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.1. that <hi>the righteous are taken away from the evil to come;</hi> as if God, when he hath deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make war upon a Nation, he removes his hoſtages of peace from it:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the wicked may take notice of the godlies morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to be a deadly meſſenger of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:120089:96"/>their future miſery.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That they may take ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable warning, God hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded miſchief againſt them, when he hath withdrawn the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſociety of his ſervants from them.</p>
                  <p>And that he hath determined ruine againſt a Land, when he accounts it not worthy to lodge his people.</p>
                  <p>The Scripture tells us,
<note place="margin">The Saints death a forerunner of the words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note> That all of the Antediluvian Patriarchs were removed to heaven, before the Judgement of the flood.</p>
                  <p>The year of the worlds drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was the year of <hi>Methuſelah</hi>'s dying. God, it ſeems, would cloſe up the number of his many dayes, and ſhut his aged eyes from beholding the ſad ſpectacle of the Creatures confuſion.</p>
                  <p>It is hiſtorically reported of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120089:96"/>S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> That the people of <hi>Hippo</hi> were not onely happy in his Preaching the Goſpel to them, but alſo by the enjoyment of his perſon amongſt them, in the time of the Arrian Perſecution in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frick:</hi> for whilſt he lived with them, nothing could be done by their cruel Adverſaries againſt them; but immediately after his death, their Town was totally ruined by the mercileſs <hi>Vandals,</hi> before the falling out of the <hi>German</hi> Miſeries by War. The Lord was pleaſed to gather many of his precious ſervants to heaven in peace.</p>
                  <p>And this hath not onely been an ancient kindneſs to the godly, (before the worſt of times) but a Modern Mercy to many of our Age, who are daily taken up, and ſecured in heaven from the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:120089:97"/>preſent dangers of ſpiritual and carnal profaneneſs, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floweth in this degenerous Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration wherein we live.
<note place="margin">We ſhould take notice of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies death &amp; its war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> Their daily removing from us, doth preſage nothing of good unto us, but bitterneſs in the latter end.</p>
                  <p>I humbly deſire this were more ſeriouſly conſidered by us, to a reforming advantage;</p>
                  <p>That however the Saints re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval be an act of Grace, as to themſelves; yet that their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were owned by us, as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſorrow, and greateſt grief.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall offer one thing to be thought upon by all: and it is ſhortly this;</p>
                  <p>Where God hath no favorites,
<note place="margin">Animad.</note> he ſhews no kindneſs, but ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth his Saints from the Tents
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:120089:97"/>the wicked, to undo them for ever.</p>
                  <p>Therefore let me this day counſel you,
<note place="margin">Counſel.</note> if ever you make account to do any thing in favour of your Countrey, and its Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſt, minde your afflicted Brethren in this juncture of their trouble.</p>
                  <p>We know not what a day may bring forth.
<note place="margin">Preſſed home.</note> This is the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Calamity, and we know not what the Lord will do for him, upon our intereſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
                  <p>What a Glory ſhall it be to us, to be the inſtrumental Saviours of our Brethren, in preſerving them more by our Prayers, than they can do themſelves by Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Animad.</note> Remember how much of the Nations happineſs is wrapt up
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120089:98"/>in their ſecurity, whoſe private Orators we are upon a publick account.</p>
                  <p>Let there be zeal in our ſpirits, to cry earneſtly for them, that it may go well with them.</p>
                  <p>Let us be wreſtling with God,
<note place="margin">Our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> whilſt they are ſtrugling with men; joyning our Forces, that they may prevail.</p>
                  <p>Let us <hi>ſowe in tears</hi> for them, that they may <hi>reap in joy</hi> for us.</p>
                  <p>I can uſe no ſtronger Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ingage your ſpirits, than to aſſure you from God, That the Glory of a Nation, are the Godly in it; they are the Pledges of its Happineſs, and therefore whenſoever or whereſoever ſuch are ingaged, Let us minde their condition, upon a publick ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:120089:98"/>
It is but folly, to fancy of our National or Perſonal ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whatever become of them: Can the Building ſtand, if the Pillars be broken?</p>
                  <p>It is a Maſter-piece of Satans policy,
<note place="margin">Satans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</note> to Charm ſome to ſuch thoughts: thus fainting their ſpirits, and friezng their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. But if the Blood of Saints;</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Bleſſing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Benefit of three Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Nations, can affect us, then let their caſes command our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to God for their aſſiſtance;
<note place="margin">We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but by prayer.</note> though they be wholly ingaged for us: yet we cannot be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſerviceable to them, than our Prayers can prevail. Let ſomething therefore be done to purpoſe with God for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:120089:99"/>of his People.</p>
                  <p>Let it be ſeriouſly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in our aſſemblings before the Lord,
<note place="margin">Animad.</note> that we make Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to him for the ſafety of his friends, and not of his enemies; ſuch who are not onely in unity with himſelf, <hi>(True and upright in their bearts)</hi> but are this day zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ingaged for his intereſt.</p>
                  <p>And if this Godly Party be joyned in the common danger,
<note place="margin">A ſcruple removed.</note> to thoſe who are of another Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, than this of Piety; men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in my Text: Let ſuch be favoured upon the Saints ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
                  <p>That thoſe poor creatures may be convinced,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is not in vain to ſerve the Lord in proſperity, and to depend upon his aſſiſtance in the day of adverſity: and</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:120089:99"/>
2. That they are debtors to the ſociety of Saints for their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance:</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Who are ſo highly prized by God, that he will ſpare the wicked for their ſake.</p>
                  <p>And however, ſome of thoſe miſerable wretches ingaged, may be paſt prayers;
<note place="margin">Jer. 7.16. &amp; 11.14. &amp; 14.11.</note> in reſpect of their perſonal demerit: yet now being occaſionally concerned in the publick ſafety, they may reap a return of prayers upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of others.</p>
                  <p>This I have added,
<note place="margin">The Saints ſpirits ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis fied.</note> to eaſe the Spirits of ſome, who are ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to intercede with God for ſuch, who poſſibly have lifted up their heart and tongue blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly againſt himſelf, his Truth, and People.</p>
                  <p>But we hope there is no ſuch ungracious Inſtruments imployed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:120089:100"/>in the preſent quarrel. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore letting the judgement of Charity paſs upon all, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it becometh our intereſt in them, to deal fervently with our God for them; ever thinking our ſelves much befriended in their deliverance.</p>
                  <p>But laſtly,
<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Our own concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this dayes addreſs.</note> I preſume it may contribute ſomewhat to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of the preſent buſineſs, if we conſider our ſelves, there is nothing of greater miſery can betide us on this ſide of heaven, then to be ſtript of the Saints com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and comfort.</p>
                  <p>They are not onely in general the Nations Glory,
<note place="margin">Our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to win tue Saints ſociety.</note> and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but each particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers incouragement and help.</p>
                  <p>There is none ſo uſeful and ſo intimate to Chriſt and his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<note place="margin">The Saints our help, every way uſeful.</note> as are thoſe of his ſpirit
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:120089:100"/>and intereſt: they are eyes to the Blinde, Feet to the Lame, Light to the Ignorant, Quickning to the Negligent, and Eaſe to the Oppreſſed. As they can ſpeak a word, ſo they can do a work of ſeaſonable ſweetneſs, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their Brethren in the evil day.</p>
                  <p>And therefore, as it is of the greateſt gain to be gathered with them; ſo it is the ſaddeſt of loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to hear of their ruine.</p>
                  <p>We reade of <hi>David,</hi> to be more afflicted with the tidings of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathans</hi> death, then ever he was troubled with the malicious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of <hi>Sauls</hi> fury.</p>
                  <p>Gods children being of the ſame ſpirit and intereſt,
<note place="margin">Our obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to Pray.</note> are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturally obliged to a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Sympathy both of loſſes and croſſes. So that they are as
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:120089:101"/>much affected with their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon indemnity, as if it were perſonal.</p>
                  <p>And as they are of the ſtricteſt unity: ſo they are of the ſweeteſt amity, for mutual aſſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>Let all this be accounted to our Brethren.
<note place="margin">God All-ſufficient for the Saints waints.</note> We are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, whoſe favour can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend them, whoſe Power can protect them, whoſe Wiſdome can direct them, whoſe Hand can help them, whoſe Heart can pity them, and whoſe Preſence is dreadful to all of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</p>
                  <p>I conceive then it ſtands us in hand to deal earneſtly with the Lord for them.</p>
                  <p>It is not the Power of Man, but the Providence of God which can ſecure and cover their head in the day of Battel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:120089:101"/>
Therefore before I cloſe up this my Exercitation,
<note place="margin">A few pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> I ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommend to your improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, theſe few particulars fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>1</label>
                     <note place="margin">Holy.</note> Let your Addreſſes to God for them be holy. Sinful Prayers are alwayes fruitleſs: as they have no power with God: ſo they never return any profit to our ſelves or others.</p>
                  <p>If we make account to do any thing for them, we muſt begin with our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David</hi> tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6. that <hi>he will waſh his hands in innocency, and then compaſs the Lords Altar,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>So that it is eaſie to conclude, There muſt be perſonal Piety to ſeaſon our devotions.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>2</label>
                     <note place="margin">Humble.</note> let your Addreſſes be humble; there is an aſſurance of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:120089:102"/>grace to ſuch, who are of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.7. It is not for Beggars to be Boaſters, but to ſubmit to the grace of the Giver: for as there is nothing in us which can commend us to God; ſo we have nothing of qualification which ſhould lift us up before him.</p>
                  <p>Hence we may determine hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to be a neceſſary ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in our Addreſſes for our ſelves or others.</p>
                  <p>Here pauſe a little,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the different entertainment of the Phariſee and the Publican; the firſt is rejected; the ſecond ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Faithful.</note> let your Addreſſes be mingled with Faith: it is folly to ſeek God, without confidence in him. He that cometh to God, muſt believe that God is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:120089:102"/>of them who ſeek him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. For as it is impoſſible without faith to pleaſe God; ſo it is to obtain any thing from him.</p>
                  <p>Hence the godly are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Orators at the Throne of Grace: For being juſtified by Faith, they have acceſs to God, ſo accompliſht by his Son, who is <hi>the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> Joh. 14.6.</p>
                  <p>It is with Chriſtians in their prayers to God,
<note place="margin">Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Saints with the Moloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians in their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes.</note> as it was with the <hi>Moloſsians</hi> in their addreſs to their king; It ſeems they behoved to take the prince in their arms, before they durſt come in his Preſence: So the Saints are to apply and embrace their Saviour by Faith, before they have acceſs to God, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with him for favour.</p>
                  <p>To conclude this alſo,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>1</label> let us
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:120089:103"/>not imagine to obtain any from God by faithleſs Addreſſes to him.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>4</label>
                     <note place="margin">Zealous.</note> let your prayers be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with zeal.</p>
                  <p>Let there be a heat in your hearts to your Brethren, and their intereſt, whilſt ye are dealing with God for them.</p>
                  <p>It ſsems they are precious to God <hi>(True and upright in their hearts)</hi> Therefore let our ſpirits be carried out with a more than ordinary ardency for them, That when deliverance is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">The Saints rejoyce when their preyers are returned for the Saints pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</note> our hearts may be mercifully cheered with the expected refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Prayers return, and triumphantly rejoyce with the voice of gladneſs; acknowledging that <hi>the right hand of the Lord hath done valiantly;</hi> he hath got him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Name by the ſafety of his
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:120089:103"/>ſervants, who lookt for his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Oh then let there be nothing wanting in our Spirits,
<note place="margin">The Point preſſed home.</note> that may effectuate ſuch a glorious end!</p>
                  <p>If Holineſs, Humility, Faith, and Zeal, can compaſs it, let us ingage all for a comfortable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. I deſire nothing more from you,
<note place="margin">From the Saints pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</note> than what hath been the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred practice of Saints in the like caſe. How ſerious they have been in the time of common danger, importuning of God by Faſting and Prayer in behalf of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly!</p>
                  <p>I could inſtance (if time did not ſtraiten me) both their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and practice to this purpoſe:
<note place="margin">Concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Tertul.</note> but for the preſent, ſparing all farther inlargement, I ſhall break off with the preſentment of a moſt excellent teſtimony from
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:120089:104"/>
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> to this purpoſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may obſerve the acting of that Spirit, which did quicken the Primitive Saints, in favour of their fellow-ſervants:
<note place="margin">Tertullian his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</note> 
                     <hi>Coimus in caetum, &amp; Congregationem, &amp; Deum quaſi manum faſtu ambiamus, (grata Deo vis eſt haec) vota fundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; coeium tundimus, Deum tangi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, miſericordiam extorquemus.</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. in Apolog.</p>
                  <p>We beſet God (ſayes he) we offer violence to him (ſuch as is acceptable to him) we pour out our Prayers, we ſend up our Cryes, we touch God, and we wreſt mercy out of his hand.</p>
                  <p>Let our Spirits be thus united, thus ingaged, thus affected, and thus exemparily directed, whilſt we are acting with God in behalf of our Brethren; and let us ſend up <hi>Davids</hi> eapreſſon with <hi>Davids</hi>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:120089:104"/>affection; ſpeaking his words with his ſympathiſing Spirit, <hi>Do well, O Lord, to thoſe who are good, and upright in their hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:105"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120089:105"/>
                  <head>BOOKS <hi>Printed for</hi> William Weekly <hi>at</hi> Ipſwich, <hi>and are to be ſold by</hi> John Rothwell, <hi>at the Fountain and Bear in Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths-Row in Cheapſide.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FEſtered Conſcence new lanced.</p>
                  <p>The good Maſters Plea, and the evil Servants Cavil.</p>
                  <p>Orthodoxal Navigation.</p>
                  <p>The Univerſal Character.</p>
                  <p>Choice Sermons of Faith, by <hi>Matthew Laurence</hi> M. A. late Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturer of <hi>Ipſwich</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
